<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="0.6.2" ident="GROBID" when="2021-08-17T12:00+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
<p>Numerous methane-emitting bottom features, such as seeps, methane clathrate hydrates (clathrates), and mud volcanoes, have been identified recently in the Black Sea. The fluxes of methane from these sources averaged over large spatial scales are unknown. Here we take advantage of the fact that the Black Sea is a semi-enclosed basin with restricted deep water circulation to establish firstorder estimates of basin-wide fluxes of methane from these sources to the water column and atmosphere. First, we measured the natural radiocarbon content of methane dissolved in the water column and emitted from seeps. The  results showed that the dominant source of methane to the water column is emitted from seeps and a smaller source is diagenetically produced in relatively modern sediments. The  results were then used to partition a basin-wide total methane budget; this analysis estimated the basin-wide flux of methane from seeps and clathrates to the water column to be <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3.60">3.60</num> to <num atMost="4.28">4.28</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure>. Second, a geochemical box model was used to calculate possible distributions of methane inputs from seeps and clathrates as well as provide additional estimates of the basin-wide flux of methane from seeps and clathrates to the water column (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.95">4.95</num> to <num atMost="5.65">5.65</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure>). © 2006 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. Keywords: methane; seeps; methane clathrate hydrates; Black Sea; methane radiocarbon; seep methane flux the north-western shelf [5].</p>
<p>These studies indicate that the Black Sea is the largest surface water reservoir of dissolved CH4 (<measure type="value"><num>96</num><measure type="MASS" unit="Tg">Tg</measure></measure>) of which <measure type="value"><num>0.066</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> are emitted into the atmosphere [1]. During the last decade, numerous seeps and mud volcanoes, emitting or capable of emitting CH4, have been identified on the shelf and slope of the northern Black Sea [7­11]. Methane clathrate hydrates (clathrates), an important global CH4 reservoir estimated to contain over <measure type="value"><num>103</num></measure> times more CH4 than the atmosphere [15], are also present in deep Black Sea sediments [11,12], and represent an unknown CH4 source. The stability of clathrates is governed by pressure, temperature, and CH4 concentration</p>
<p>and b) CH4 that is produced diagenetically in relatively modern sediments and released to the water column. We measured the natural radiocarbon content of CH4 (14C­ CH4) in the Black Sea (Fig. 1, Table 1) and performed a 14C­CH4 isotope mass balance to determine the fraction of CH4 emitted to the water column that is from seeps and decomposing clathrates. (Previous 14C­CH4 measurements from seeps and clathrates show that they are both devoid of natural radiocarbon [25­27], so radiocarbon measurements cannot distinguish between CH4 released from seeps and clathrates; for brevity, we use the term "seep" to apply to both.) This fraction was multiplied by the total source of CH4 to the Black Sea, resulting in an estimate of the flux of CH4 from seeps to the water column (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3.60">3.60</num> to <num atMost="4.28">4.28</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg CH4 yr-1</measure></measure>) and atmosphere (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.05">0.05</num> to <num atMost="0.21">0.21</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg CH4 yr-1</measure></measure>).</p>
<p>The modeling studies involved modifying a timedependent geochemical box model [28] to include a source term for CH4 emitted from seeps and adhere to the parameters of the Black Sea. The modeling results estimate depth distributions and magnitudes (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.95">4.95</num> to <num atMost="5.65">5.65</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg CH4 yr-1</measure></measure>) of the input of CH4 from seeps to the water column.</p>
<p>2.1.1. Total methane budget The total Black Sea CH4 budget was assembled from CH4 concentration and anaerobic oxidation of CH4 (AOM) rate measurements made during the 1988 U.S.Turkey Black Sea Expedition [1] (Table 1). Measurements of CH4 dissolved in the water column (concentration and AOM rates) were restricted to a central station (43°05N, 34°00E, <measure type="value"><num>200</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth) well-removed from shelves, and were intended to represent a basin-wide integration of processes affecting the Black Sea CH4 distribution and budget. Distributions of CH4 concentration in sediment cores were measured at a shelf station (41°35.5N, 28° 56.92E,<measure type="value"><num>170</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth) and a deep station (43°04.82N, 33°58.88E, <measure type="value"><num>2212</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth) (Fig. 1). Water column profiles of CH4 concentration and AOM rates were assumed to represent average Black Sea values so that a first-order estimate of the Black Sea CH4 budget could be established. This budget was based on the following sinks of CH4: measured water column and sediment rates of AOM, calculated gas evasion rates to the atmosphere, and export by the Bosporus outflow (Table 2). Reeburgh et al. [1] determined that the dominant sink of CH4, AOM in the water column, is about <measure type="value"><num>70-fold</num></measure> larger than the next largest sink of CH4, evasion at the air : sea interface.</p>
<p>This budget assumed that the CH4 concentration in the waters of the Black Sea is in steady-state [1], so the total loss of CH4 must be balanced with a CH4 source of the same magnitude (Table 2). Only CH4 produced diagenetically in sediments was considered a source in the original budget [1]. Thermodynamic arguments indicate that there can be no large-scale production of CH4 in the water column so long as sulfate reduction is occurring [1,29,30]. Measurements by Albert et al. [31] show that sulfate reduction occurs in the water column of the Black Sea at nM day-1 rates, so we conclude that large-scale methanogenesis cannot occur in the anoxic Black Sea water column. A minor contribution of CH4 to the water column may be from zooplankton guts and</p>
<p>Rate:<measure type="value"><num>9.7</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mmol m-2 yr-1" >mmol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> Extent: <measure type="value"><num>4.23 × 1011</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="m2">m2</measure></measure> m2 Water column oxidation Upper <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (aerobic/anaerobic) Rate: <measure type="value"><num>0.36</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="nM yr-1">nM yr-1</measure></measure> Extent: <measure type="value"><num>5.3 × 1016</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">L</measure></measure> Below <measure type="value"><num>100</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (anaerobic) Rate: <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="M yr-1">M yr-1</measure></measure> Extent:<measure type="value"><num>4.8 × 1017</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">L</measure></measure> Oxidation by abyssal sediments Rate: <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mmol m-2 yr-1">mmol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> Extent: <measure type="value"><num>2.3 × 1011</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="m2">m2</measure></measure> Outflow at Bosporus Rate: <measure type="value"><num>1.9 × 1014</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="L yr-1">L yr-1</measure></measure> Extent: <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure></p>
<p>Sources Shelf/slope sediments 
Rate: <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> Extent: <measure type="value"><num>1.1 × 1011</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="m2">m2</measure></measure> Seeps and clathrates (from this study: combined measurement and modeling results) Rate: <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.53">0.53</num> to <num atMost="0.84">0.84</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure></p>
<p>Given the relatively high Black Sea water column CH4 concentrations (M) (Fig. 2), zooplankton guts and fecal pellet microenvironments likely provide <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total source of CH4 to the water column.</p>
<p>At the shelf station, the CH4 concentration measured in a sediment core displayed a concave up distributio which shows that AOM is occurring [43]. A small positive CH4 concentration gradient between the surface sediments and the water column indicates that sediments on the shelf are a source of CH4 to the water column. In contrast, CH4 concentrations in sediments at the deep station are lower than in the adjacent overlying waters, indicating that these sediments are consuming CH4 from the water column. This was confirmed by AOM rate measurements using 14C-labelled CH4 [1]. The Reeburgh et al. budget assumed that sediments below the anoxic : oxic interface (<measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>) and above the continental slope-abyssal plane transition (<measure type="value"><num>1500</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>) were the source of CH4 to the water column [1]. Given this source interval, a flux of CH4 from sediments of <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> is needed to balance the sinks and maintain a steady-state CH4 concentration in the water column. However, they determined the flux of CH4 from the shelf core to be <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> leaving <measure type="value"><num>86.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the balancing source flux not quantified [1]. Subsequent measurements of CH4 concentration profiles in sediment cores [5,6] indicate that the diffusive flux of CH4 from sediments to the water.</p>
<p>Fig. 2. Measured Black Sea CH4 concentration (M) and isotope  data in the water column. The 13CCH4 data is expressed vs. VPDB (Vienna Peedee belemnite) standard. The 14CCH4 data is expressed as percent Modern Carbon (pMC) [47]. By convention [47], all radiocarbon results are normalized to 13C. Samples were collected in the () central Black Sea water column in <measure type="value"><date when=
"1988-07-01">July 1988</date></measure> [1,50] and () western Black Sea water column in <measure type="value"><date when=
"2001-05-01">May 2001</date></measure>. Precision of ±1 for the: 1) CH4 concentration measurements is <measure type="value"><num>3­4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> based on replicate analyses of samples, 2) 13C­CH4 measurements is 0.3 based on replicate analyses of standard samples, and 3) 14C­CH4 measurements is <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num><measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>. Error bars for the 13C­CH4 and 14C­CH4 measurements are less than the width of the data points. A previously published multi-box model [28] was used to quantify the depth distributions of the inputs of CH4[S] and to provide additional estimates of the basin-wide flux of CH4[S].</p>
<p>His model was modified to have box thicknesses of <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>, to not consider depths less than <measure type="value"><num>150</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> due to low water column CH4 concentrations and oxic conditions in the shallow surface waters, and to match the parameters of the Black Sea (bathymetry and eddy diffusion coefficients).</p>
<p>The model was initiated with no CH4 in the basin and was run for <measure type="value"><num>200</num><measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure> to reach steady-state. The inputs of CH4[S] were varied until the modeled CH4 concentration profile matched the measurements made in year 2001. LEFT PANEL: The model was assigned inputs of CH4[D] (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="150">150</num> to <num atMost="1550">1550</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> , <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1550">1550</num> to <num atMost="2050">2050</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure>, <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2050">2050</num><num atMost="2150">2150</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>0.02</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure>). The following model results are displayed for CH4 concentration and inputs of CH4[S]: (solid black line) model dependent upon the CH4 concentration data represented by (), (dashed line) model dependent upon a uniform CH4 concentration profile of <measure type="value"><num>13.32</num><measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure> below <measure type="interval"><num atMost="700">700</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>  depth, (dotted line) model dependent upon a uniform CH4 concentration profile of <measure type="value"><num>11.82</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION">M</measure></measure> below <measure type="value"><num>700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth, (solid gray line) model dependent upon average values of CH4 concentration.</p>
<p>The inputs of seep and clathrate CH4 represented by the dashed, dotted, and solid gray lines are not plotted in histogram style only to increase legibility. RIGHT PANEL: The model was dependent upon the CH4 concentration data represented by () in the left panel. The solid black line represents the model results with the assigned inputs of CH4[D] used in the left panel. The dashed line represents the model results with the assigned inputs of CH4[D] as suggested by Reeburgh et al. [1]. The dotted line represents the model results with the assigned inputs of CH4[D] as suggested by Reeburgh et al. [1] and with an additional input of <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2050">2050</num> to <num atMost="2150">2150</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>.</p>
<p>2.1.2. Methane concentration, 13C, and radiocarbon measurements
Water samples were collected from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2001-05-26">May 26</date> to <date to-iso="2001-06-03">June 3, 2001</date></measure>, on board the R/V Knorr within a <measure type="value"><num>4.24</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> radius of a station located in the western section of the Black Sea (42°30.21N, 30°45.21E, <measure type="value"><num>2100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>) (Table 1, Fig. 1). Concentrations of CH4 (M) were measured with a headspace equilibration technique based on Henry's Law. Samples were prepared for seawater CH4 concentration analyses by filling <measure type="value"><num>120</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="cc">cc</measure></measure> serum vials directly from Niskin bottles. After the seawater vials were sealed with stoppers and crimp caps, a <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="cc">cc</measure></measure> headspace of ultrahigh-purity helium was introduced by displacing an equivalent volume of sample. The vials were vigorously shaken and allowed to equilibrate for <measure type="value"><num>12</num><measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> . Shipboard CH4 concentration analyses were performed by analyzing two <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="cc">cc</measure></measure> aliquots of the headspace with gas chromatography and flame ionization detection (GC-Mini 2; Shimadzu Corp). The results have been corrected for the amount of CH4 still dissolved in solution using Bunsen solubility coefficients established by Yamamoto et al. [44] (Fig. 2).</p>
<p>Lamont radon stripping boards [45,46] were modified to quantitatively extract and trap the CH4 dissolved in seawater for natural isotopic analysis. For each sample, an evacuated <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">L</measure></measure> glass carboy was filled with <measure type="value"><num>19</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">L</measure></measure> of seawater directly from Niskin bottles. The carboy was connected to a stripping board which circulated helium through the seawater sample to extract the dissolved CH4. The extracted CH4 was trapped at liquid nitrogen temperature in a stainless steel U-trap, filled with a molecular sieve. (Due to low water column concentrations of CH4 at and above <measure type="value"><num>300</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth, CH4 was extracted from two carboys (<measure type="value"><num>38</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">L</measure></measure>) for the shallowest samples.) The traps were returned to UC Irvine where the CH4 was extracted, purified, and analyzed for the natural content of 13C and radiocarbon. The entire CH4 collection, extraction, and analysis procedures are quantitative and the backgrounds are small (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.528</num> ± <num type="range">0.39</num><measure type="AMOUNT_OF_SUBSTANCE" unit="mol">mol</measure></measure> of CH4 with radiocarbon content 14C / C = <measure type="interval"><num type="base">96.1</num>±<num type="range">0.3</num><measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure> (percent Modern Carbon) [47]) relative to the average sample size (<measure type="value"><num>228</num><measure type="AMOUNT_OF_SUBSTANCE" unit="mol">mol</measure></measure>). Details of the isotope procedures (apparatus, techniques, blank determinations, precision, and the lack of isotope fractionation) are presented in Kessler and Reeburgh [48].</p>
<p>Second, the concentration of CH4 dissolved in the water column is on average <measure type="value"><num>11.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> higher is the western BlackS ea (measured in 2001) than in the central Black Sea (measured in 1988) (Fig. 2). If we assume that the CH4 concentration values measured in 1988 and 2001 represent average values for the entire basin and not spatial heterogeneities in CH4 concentration, then the CH4 concentration has increased by <measure type="value"><num>11.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> over a <measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure> period. This increase in CH4 inventory would cause the 13C of CH4 dissolved in the water column to decrease by <measure type="interval"><num type="base">1.4</num>±<num type="range">0.7</num></measure> over this <measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure> period [49]. While this difference is small, our measurements of 13C­CH4 are indistinguishable from those conducted <measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure> ago [50].</p>
<p>The possibility exists of non-steady-state conditions above the shallow shelves (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num> to <num atMost="500">500</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth) where episodic intrusions of CH4 from seeps influence the water column CH4 concentration. However, this region of possible non-steady-state accounts for only <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total volume of the Black Sea [52].</p>
<p>The results of our 14C­CH4 measurements on gas emitted from seeps were unexpected; all samples of CH4 emitted from seeps (CH4[S]) contain measurable amounts of radiocarbon (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">5.02</num>±<num type="range">0.4</num><measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure> ; <measure type="value"><num>24</num><measure type="TIME" unit="kA 14C BP">kA 14C BP</measure></measure> (thousand radiocarbon years Before Present)).</p>
<p>Their results (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="8.5">8.5</num> to <num atMost="10.6">10.6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="kA 14C BP">kA 14C BP</measure></measure> or <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="34.7">34.7</num> to <num atMost="26.7">26.7</num><measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>) were calculated from measurements of CH4 (13C), seawater bicarbonate (13C and radiocarbon), and the carbonate structures formed around <measure type="interval"><num>230</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> deep CH4 seeps (13C and radiocarbon) located ca. <measure type="value"><num>26</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> south-east of our seep site. The process of anaerobically oxidizing CH4 to total CO2 causes significant isotopic fractionation in both the reactant and the product.</p>
<p><measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> factors cause the upper range reported by Gulin et al. [8] to increase to <measure type="value"><num>18.2</num><measure type="TIME" unit="kA 14C BP">kA 14C BP</measure></measure> (or <measure type="value"><num>10.4</num> <measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>), and show how sensitive their indirect analysis is to parameter changes. There are no 14CCH4 measurements in the Black Sea of CH4 produced diagenetically in sediments (CH4[D]). However, CH4 formed at relatively shallow depths in sediments can diffuse into the water column and should contain measurable amounts of radiocarbon (pMC N 0) and possibly a radiocarbon content influenced by atmospheric nuclear weapons testing (pMC N 100). Recent 14CCH4 measurements in the sediments of the Cariaco Basin [57] and Skan Bay, AK [27] show that near-modern radiocarbon values are found in near-surface sediments and the 14C content decreases with depth; this indicates that CH4 is produced locally and is not dominated by CH4 diffusing up from deep sediments [55,58]. Previous radiocarbon measurements aimed at determining the Black Sea sediment chronology show that in the interval of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num> to <num atMost="50">50</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> depth, the total organic carbon and total carbonate carbon ranges from <measure type="interval"><num atMost="105">105</num> to <num atLeast="63">63</num> <measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure> [59,60]. Decadal turnover times for CH4[D], determined from concentration and oxidation rate measurements of CH4 [1,5,6], indicate that CH4[D] likely has a similar radiocarbon signature to its substrates, the total carbon material. Since CH4 dissolved in the Black Sea water column also has decadal turnover times [1], the 14 CH4 results indicate that the source of CH4 to the water column is a mixture of CH4[S] and CH4[D].</p>
<p>2.1.3. Partitioning the total flux of methane to the water column
To estimate the magnitude of the flux of CH4[S] to the water column, first we determine the fraction of the total source of CH4 to the water column that is emitted from seeps and then we multiply that fraction by the total flux of Black Sea CH4 to the water column (<measure type="value"><num>4.72</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> = sum of the sinks in Table 2). We used a radiocarbon isotopic mass balance to determine the fraction of the total CH4 source this is emitted from seeps (Eq. 2).</p>
<p>Here, F is the fraction of the source of CH4 that is emitted from seeps and pMCS, pMCD, and pMCW are the 14C­CH4 contents of CH4[S] (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">5.02</num>±<num type="range">0.4</num> <measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>), CH4[D], and CH4 dissolved in the water column (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">15.7</num> ± <num type="range">6.75</num> <measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>), respectively. We have no direct measurements of the 14C­CH4 content of CH4[D]. Based on radiocarbon measurements of total organic and carbonate carbon in the sediment [59,60], the most likely radiocarbon content of CH4[D] is between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="63">63</num> and <num atMost="105">105</num> <measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>. We have placed conservative bounds on the radiocarbon signature of CH4[D] in the four cases presented in Table 3. This analysis indicates that the basin-wide flux of CH4[S] to the water column is likely between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3.60">3.60</num> and <num atMost="4.28">4.28</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> (Table 3).</p>
<p>For CH4 dissolved in the near surface waters of the Black Sea, <measure type="value"><num>0.066</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> evade into the atmosphere (Table 2) [1]. The average 14C­CH4 content in the surface 250 m of the water column is <measure type="interval"><num type="base">13.7</num> ± <num type="range">3.7</num> <measure type="PERCENT_MODERN_CARBON" unit="pMC">pMC</measure></measure>. We estimate a range of fluxes of CH4[S] to the atmosphere in the Black Sea (Table 3) for CH4 dissolved in the near surface waters that evades to the atmosphere (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.05">0.05</num> to <num atMost="0.06">0.06</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure>); bubbles that enter the atmosphere are not considered in this estimate. Dimitrov [7] found this to be a substantial flux (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.03">0.03</num> to <num atMost="0.15">0.15</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg CH4 yr-1</measure></measure>) compared with our flux of dissolved CH4, so to account for the shallow water bubble flux, we adjust the total flux of CH4[S] to the atmosphere in the Black Sea to <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.05">0.05</num> to <num atMost="0.21">0.21</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure>.</p>
<p>2.2. Modeling the flux of methane from seeps
We apply a time-dependent geochemical box model [28] to the anoxic region (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="150">150</num> to <num atMost="2150">2150</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth) of the Black Sea to quantify the depth distribution of inputs of CH4[S] as well as to provide an additional estimate of the basin-wide input of CH4[S]. The model includes a source term for CH4[S], assumes the concentration of CH4 dissolved in the water column is in steady-state, uses the Black Sea bathymetry [52], and assigns each box a thickness of <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>. The model incorporates the specific rate of AOM in the water column (<measure type="value"><num>0.06</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="yr-1">yr-1</measure></measure>) [1]. (Rates of AOM in the water column have been shown to increase linearly with CH4 concentration [61]. Specific rates of AOM are normalized to CH4 concentration, so that they may be accurately applied to different concentration regions.) Also, the model includes a term for the consumption of CH4 from the water column by abyssal sediments (<measure type="value"><num>0.1</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mmol m-2 yr-1">mmol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure>) (Table 2) [1]. Our multi-box model is one-dimensional (vertical), so the possibility exists that there are regions in the area defined by each box where CH4 is being inputted to the water column from sediments and separate regions where CH4 is being consumed from the water column by the sediments. Initially, we assigned inputs of CH4[D] to the water column over the depth interval of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="150">150</num> to <num atMost="1550">1550</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>, at a rate of <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure>, as suggested by Reeburgh et al. [1] (Table 2).</p>
<p>The model was initiated with no CH4 in the Black Sea water column and was run for <measure type="value"><num>200</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure> (time step = <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure>), significantly longer than the model predicts is necessary to reach steady-state. The inputs of CH4[S] were varied until the modeled concentrations of CH4 dissolved in the water column agreed with the year 2001 western Black Sea measurements to less than <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> on average. No isotopic data is input into the model, so the newly predicted inputs of CH4[S] and the assigned values of CH4[D] can be used to model a 14C­CH4 profile in the water column (Fig. 2). This model predicts a 14C­CH4 profile containing significantly less radiocarbon than our measurements in the deep Black Sea.</p>
<p>We conclude that the deep waters of the Black Sea must have an additional source of CH4 with relatively modern radiocarbon contents. To account for this additional source of relatively "modern" CH4, we conducted two modeling experiments where we manually increased the deep basin sources of CH4[D] beyond what was suggested by Reeburgh et al. [1] (Fig. 2.). Inputs of CH4[S] are predicted at most depths between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="250">250</num> and <num atMost="2150">2150</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (Fig. 2), consistent with the distribution of known seeps, clathrates, mud volcanoes, and seabed pockmarks (Fig. 1) [8,12,14]. The model-predicted input profile of CH4[S] shows local maxima or minima at <measure type="list"><num>700</num>, <num>1100</num>, and <num>1700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth consistent with congruent fluctuations in the mean values of CH4 concentration at similar depths. However, the uncertainty in our concentration measurements is such that a uniform CH4 concentration profile below <measure type="value"><num>700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth is possible. To account for this possibility, we have conducted two additional modeling experiments dependent upon uniform CH4 concentration values (below <measure type="value"><num>700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth) at either the lower end (<measure type="value"><num>11.82</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure>) or the upper end (<measure type="value"><num>13.32</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure>) of the standard deviations of our CH4 concentration measurements. These "uniform CH4 concentration" models predict more uniform distributions for the inputs of CH4[S] (Fig. 2). Due to the large predicted inputs of CH4[S], this model is relatively insensitive to the water column eddy diffusion coefficients. Changing the eddy diffusion coefficients from <measure type="UNKNOWN"><num atLeast="1">1</num> to <num atMost="4">4</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm2 s-1">cm2 s-1</measure></measure> in the anoxic region of the Black Sea only changes the final results by <measure type="value"><num>3.7</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> on average. Also, CH4[S] released below the clathrate stability zone (<measure type="value"><num>700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>) will partially resist dissolution due to the formation of a clathrate mantle around the bubbles</p>
<p>If CH4[S] only dissolved in waters above <measure type="value"><num>700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> depth, eddy diffusion in the water column could not maintain CH4 concentration and radiocarbon profiles, so bubbles must dissolve in deep waters or CH4 must be added in solution. Averaged over the entire basin, our results indicate that<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.95">4.95</num> to <num atMost="5.65">5.65</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.73">0.73</num> to <num atMost="0.84">0.84</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol m-2 yr-1</measure></measure>) of CH4[S] are being added to the water column. Since this multi-box model is one-dimensional (vertical), it assumes that the CH4 concentration profile measured in the western Black Sea water column is representative of average values for the entire basin. In Section 2.1. Measuring the flux of methane from seeps, we assumed that the CH4 concentration profile measured in the central Black Sea water column is representative of average values for the entire basin, again to estimate the basin-wide inputs of CH4[S]. Since the CH4 concentration profile measured in the western Black Sea water column is on average <measure type="value"><num>11.5</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> greater than in the central Black Sea, these separate estimates of the basin-wide inputs of CH4[S] likely bound the true value.</p>
<p>3. Conclusions
The contribution of decomposing clathrates to the global CH4 budget remains a major uncertainty [63]. Substantial microbial oxidation in adjacent sediments and overlying waters precludes the use of stable isotopes of CH4 to identify the fraction of CH4 dissolved in the water column or sediment that is released from clathrates. Rehder et al. [19] measured the rate of dissolution of synthetic CH4 clathrate in the clathrate stability zone (P, T) in an advecting field of seawater that was undersaturated with respect to CH4 concentration. Since natural clathrates are usually located within a sediment matrix surrounded by CH4-rich or CH4saturated fluids, the Rehder et al. rates place an upper bound on the decomposing clathrate contribution (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">11670</num>±<num type="range">950</num><measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol CH4 m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> ). Presuming the fluxes of CH4[S] estimated in this study are all of clathrate origin, the Black Sea clathrate decomposition rate is <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.53">0.53</num> to <num atMost="0.84">0.84</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mol m-2 yr-1">mol CH4 m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> , or <measure type="value"><num>105-fold</num></measure> smaller.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we have estimated the basin-wide flux of CH4 emitted from seeps and decomposing clathrates to the water column and atmosphere in the Black Sea. The radiocarbon results indicate that the flux of CH4 to the water column is dominated by emissions from seeps and decomposing clathrates. Our measurements and modeling studies indicate that between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3.60">3.60</num> to <num atMost="5.65">5.65</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> of CH4 emitted from seeps and decomposing clathrates enter the Black Sea water column and<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.05">0.05</num> to <num atMost="0.21">0.21</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure> escape to the atmosphere. These estimates of the fluxes of CH4 emitted from seeps and decomposing clathrates to the Black Sea may be refined with longterm sampling programs; multiple sites can be established characterizing the entire Black Sea where high precision measurements of CH4 concentration, rates of AOM, and natural isotopes of CH4 are routinely made.</p>
  </text>
</tei>
