<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="0.6.2" ident="GROBID" when="2021-08-17T12:00+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
<p>Methane emissions from the sea floor a ect methane inputs into the atmosphere1, ocean acidification and de-oxygenation2,3, the distribution of chemosynthetic communities and energy resources. Global methane flux from seabed cold seeps has only been estimated for continental shelves4, at<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="8">8</num>to<num atMost="65">65</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Tg yr-1">Tg yr-1</measure></measure>, yet other parts of marine continental margins are also emitting methane. The US Atlantic margin has not been considered an area of widespread seepage, with only three methane seeps recognized seaward of the shelf break. However, massive upper-slope seepage related to gas hydrate degradation has been predicted for the southern part of this margin5, even though this process has previously only been recognized in the Arctic2,6,7. Here we use multibeam water-column backscatter data that cover<measure type="value"><num>94,000</num><measure type="AREA" unit="km2">km2</measure></measure> of sea floor to identify about <measure type="value"><num>570</num></measure> gas plumes at water depths between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num>-<num atMost="1700">1,700</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> between Cape Hatteras and Georges Bank on the northern US Atlantic passive margin. About <measure type="value"><num>440</num></measure> seeps originate at water depths that bracket the updip limit for methane hydrate stability. Contemporary upper-slope seepage there may be triggered by ongoing warming of intermediate waters, but authigenic carbonates observed imply that emissions have continued for more than <measure type="value"><num>1.000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> at some seeps. Extrapolating the upper-slope seep density on this margin to the global passive margin system, we suggest that tens of thousands of seeps could be discoverable.</p>
<p>The bubbles that comprise the plumes have not been sampled, but most likely contain methane. Microbial methane, which is produced during the degradation of organic matter in the sea floor, is widespread in the sediments of many continental margins beneath the sulphate reduction zone, where anaerobic oxidation of methane (AOM) is most active. Some chemosynthetic organisms (for example, Bathymodiolus mussels, bacterial mats) observed during ROV dives are metabolically dependent on methane or on hydrogen sulphide, a by-product of AOM. AOM also produces authigenic carbonates in sediments, and the extensive exhumed carbonates discovered at some seeps imply methane emissions, although not necessarily continuously, for more than <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="kyr">kyr</measure></measure> on the basis of carbonate growth rates measured elsewhere (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.4">0.4</num>–<num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr-1">cm kyr-1</measure></measure> ; ref. 11). High methane concentrations (<measure type="value"><num>1.75 × 104</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="ppm">ppm</measure></measure> at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6.6">6.6</num>–<num atMost="72.6">72.6</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> below the sea floor) were encountered in sediments on the upper slope offshore New Jersey12. In the water column, methane concentrations reach <measure type="value"><num>100</num><measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> or more in Hudson Canyon13 and on the Virginia outer shelf14, although seafloor seeps and/or water-column plumes were never identified. Quantitative resource assessments for the margin yield<measure type="value"><num>6.14 × 1014</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="m3">m3</measure></measure> methane sequestered in gas hydrates15, which is a frozen form of water and concentrated methane stable in sediments at relatively low temperatures and moderate pressures.</p>
<p>The water-column gas plumes on the northern USAM originate at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num>–<num atMost="1700">1,700</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure> and are distributed in <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="69">69</num>–<num atMost="87">87</num></measure> seep clusters, as well as at solitary seeps. The patchy along-margin seep distribution reflects variations in sediment lithology, erosional history, methane availability, and interaction with ocean currents. The most notable feature is the concentration of ><measure type="value"><num>240</num></measure> plumes on the upper continental slope between Washington and Baltimore canyons (along-margin distance <measure type="value"><num>92</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) compared with none (except in Hudson Canyon) in the sector stretching <measure type="value"><num>415</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> from Wilmington Canyon (Mid-Atlantic Bight) to Atlantis Canyon (Southern New England margin). On the basis of the analysis of <measure type="value"><num>3.2×105</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> of multichannel seismic data15, the plume-free Wilmington to Atlantis canyons sector has thinner post-Cretaceous sediment cover (hundreds of metres compared with <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1000">1,000</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>), higher sand content (particularly south of Hudson Canyon) that would promote diffuse (non-seep) gas emission, and lower sediment methane charge than the Washington to Baltimore canyons sector.</p>
<p>Pleistocene shelf-edge deposits16 that may trap methane. In contrast, the shelf-break to upper-slope Pleistocene section is strongly eroded and/or missing east of Atlantis Canyon and especially south of Wilmington Canyon16, and older, permeable strata that intersect the sea floor may feed seeps.</p>
<p>At a finer scale, seeps are spatially associated with canyons, occurring on promontories overlooking shelf-break canyon heads, on ridges within canyons, or where canyons have eroded upperslope deposits (Fig. 2a,c). Canyon incision downward into older strata and landward into the upper slope and shelf break may physically disrupt gas hydrate or free gas deposits (Fig. 3). Hudson Canyon, the largest on the margin, has long been suspected to host seeps13. We discovered at least <measure type="value"><num>25</num></measure> seeps in the canyon's thalweg at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="497">497</num>–<num atMost="580">580</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>, which is a depth range spanning the updip limit (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="505">505</num>–<num atMost="585">585</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>) of the gas hydrate stability zone17 (GHSZ) calculated from observed bottom-water temperatures (BWTs). At least <measure type="value"><num>25</num></measure> more seeps occur between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="97">97</num>–<num atMost="368">368</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>.
<measure type="value"><num>Fifty-seven</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="percent">per cent</measure></measure> of USAM plumes originate between Cape Hatteras and Hudson Canyon at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="250">250</num>–<num atMost="600">600</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>, which suggests a link to the dynamics of the GHSZ. The GHSZ thins to vanishing on upper continental slopes, rendering this part of the deepwater gas hydrate system sensitive to complete dissociation as impinging intermediate waters warm18.</p>
<p>Figure 2 | Seep and pockmark distributions and seafloor photographs at upper-slope and deepwater seep sites o shore Virginia. a,b, Seeps (colour-coded as in Fig. 1) and pockmarks17 (white) with bathymetry contoured at <measure type="value"><num>200</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> intervals north (a) and south (b) of Norfolk Canyon. Nominal updip limit of gas hydrate stability zone is <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="505">505</num>–<num atMost="575">575</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>. In a, note the paired shelf-edge/upper-slope seeps and upper-slope seeps arrayed around a broad, pockmark-free canyon head. In b, the inset shows water-column plume visualization at <measure type="value"><num>1400</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>, deflected westward by currents.</p>
<p>Comparing the locations of mapped plumes (<measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> resolution) and those of more than <measure type="value"><num>5,000</num></measure> upper-slope Pleistocene to Holocene pockmarks (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>–<num atMost="20">20</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> resolution)17 yields only <measure type="value"><num>17</num></measure> pockmarks occurring within <measure type="value"><num>70</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> of a seep. All such features are in the Washington to Baltimore canyons sector (<measure type="interval"><num atMost="95">95</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>), which is characterized by <measure type="value"><num>250</num></measure> plumes and <measure type="value"><num>630</num></measure> pockmarks in the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="150">150</num>–<num atMost="600">600</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure> interval. The high density of pockmarks and seeps, and not a causal relationship between contemporary seepage and pockmark formation, may explain the spatial proximity of some pockmarks and seeps in this sector.</p>
<p>perturbations cannot be attributed directly to the Gulf Stream, which peels northeastward towards Georges Bank at these latitudes. Warm-core rings spawned by the Gulf Stream sometimes become trapped on the New Jersey continental slope (no seeps) and occasionally affect the southern New England shelf break20 (some seeps). Currents offshore New York and New England are also influenced by the North Atlantic Oscillation, which has experienced a strong positive shift since the 1970s (ref. 21). The positive North Atlantic Oscillation state causes warm Atlantic slope waters to dominate over cold, southward-flowing Labrador waters, increasing BWT at intermediate water depths. Such oceanographic processes may explain decadal-scale forcing for upper-slope seepage on the New England margin, but not as far south as the Washington to Wilmington canyons sector. At intra-annual timescales, the sparse data available there indicate upper-slope BWT variations of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> or more22, which could repeatedly destabilize upper-slope gas hydrates.
The backscatter analysis also reveals <measure type="value"><num>38</num></measure> new deepwater (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1,000">1,000</num>–<num atMost="1,700">1,700</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>) seeps. Some are solitary (for example, within the Currituck slide scar), but most occur in sublinear clusters.</p>
<p>by upper-slope seeps for the base case calculation. Even if this represents only <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the methane released in the sediments by dissociating gas hydrates (assuming <measure type="value"><num>80</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> consumed by AOM and <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> retained in sediments) and the flux continues unabated for <measure type="value"><num>104</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure>, dissociation would have liberated only <measure type="value"><num>0.0014</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="Gt">Gt</measure></measure> CH4 that was previously sequestered in gas hydrates. As upper-slope gas hydrates in this sector are estimated to sequester many times more methane.</p>
<p>The approach used to map widespread methane seepage on the northern USAM can be applied to other regional-scale surveys. The northern USAM averages <measure type="value"><num>0.46</num></measure> upper-slope seeps per kilometre between Cape Hatteras and Georges Bank (<measure type="value"><num>440</num></measure> seeps in <measure type="value"><num>950</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>). Extrapolating to the <measure type="value"><num>6 × 10^4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> length of global passive margins implies that <measure type="value"><num>29,500</num></measure> upper-slope seeps may be discoverable in areas with appropriate lithology, geologic history, sufficient methane charge, and warming BWT conditions. Such seeps would represent a source of global seabed methane emissions that have not been fully accounted for in previous carbon budgets.</p>
<p>Pressure (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>–<num atMost="17">17</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure></measure>) and BWT (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3.5">3.5</num>–<num atMost="4.5">4.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">◦C</measure></measure>) place these seeps far within the GHSZ. Although gas hydrate was discovered during ROV exploration of some deepwater seeps, BWT is so stable at these depths that gas hydrate degradation is an unlikely primary cause for methane plumes. On the southeastern US margin8, deepwater seeps occur where high-thermal-conductivity salt diapirs cause warming of overlying, hydrate-bearing sediments23, but salt diapirs have never been mapped on the northern USAM continental slope. Most of the deepwater seeps occur in eroded sections of the mid-slope, where gas migrates through fractured, shallowly buried Eocene rocks.</p>
<p>About <measure type="value"><num>90</num></measure> seeps are identified landward of the shelf break (<measure type="value"><num>180</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>), an area that was minimally surveyed. Most of the shelfal gas plumes detected with the multibeam surveys are near canyon heads, and a <measure type="value"><num>few</num></measure> shelfal seep clusters are paired with nearby upper-slope seeps (Fig. 2a), implying updip gas migration. Mid-shelf seeps (<measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>) south of Nantucket occur in sediments known to host a shallow Pleistocene-aged groundwater system24, and at least <measure type="value"><num>12</num></measure> seeps at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="97">97</num>–<num atMost="138">138</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure> in the upper reaches of Hudson Canyon may also be loci of groundwater discharge25. Such discharge must entrain gas and/or be significantly colder than surrounding waters to produce the observed water-column backscatter signal. For this data set, <measure type="value"><num>1.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the estimated methane flux originates at shelfal seeps, which are the most critical for atmospheric methane inputs1. More extensive surveys will be required to thoroughly map shelfal seep distributions and to assess ocean to atmospheric methane flux.</p>
<p>Methane emissions from the northern USAM seeps are conservatively estimated at, corresponding to ∼<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="15">15</num>–<num atMost="90">90</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Mg yr-1">Mg yr-1</measure></measure>  <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.96 × 106">0.96 × 106</num>–<num atMost="5.66 × 106">5.66 × 106</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mol yr-1">mol yr-1</measure></measure>. The range in the estimates reflects variations in bubble sizes, emission rates, number of emission sites per seep, and BWT scenarios (Supplementary Table 3). The estimated flux is a fraction of that determined from careful quantification in <measure type="value"><num>12</num></measure> seep areas on the Makran margin26 (∼<measure type="interval"><num type="base">40</num> ± <num range="32 ×106">32 ×106</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mol yr-1">mol yr-1</measure></measure> ). The greatest uncertainty in the northern USAM flux calculation is the number of emission sites that contribute to a single water-column gas plume. The seeps explored by the ROV are associated with the best quality (strongest) and thus highest flux27 plumes, yet the number of seafloor emission sites varied from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num> to more than <num atMost="15">15</num></measure> (Supplementary Table 2). Where <measure type="value"><num>few</num></measure> emission sites were found, the ROV probably missed some or surveyed when some were dormant.</p>
<p>Upper-slope USAM seeps contribute <measure type="value"><num>67</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total estimated emissions, implying that substantial methane is injected into intermediate waters, where it may enhance oxidation28. Between Washington and Baltimore canyons, <measure type="value"><num>13.8</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Mg yr-1">Mg yr-1</measure></measure> CH4 is emitted.</p>
<p>The mount of methane contained in a single bubble is determined from the compressible gas law (n = ZPV/RT ), where n is the number of moles of methane in a spherical bubble of volume V emitted at a given temperature (BWT) T in Kelvin and hydrostatic pressure P in pascals (ref. 29), Z is the compressibility of methane29, and R is the universal gas constant. Multiplying by an assumed number of emission sites and rate of bubble production at each seep yields estimated methane emissions for a seep, and contributions are summed to determine total annual emissions, assuming that the bubbles contain pure methane (<measure type="value"><num>16.04</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="g mol-1">g mol-1</measure></measure>) at the sea floor. BWTs at greater than <measure type="value"><num>250</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure> were determined using a high-order polynomial fit to CTD (conductivity, temperature and depth) temperatures recorded within <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of full ocean depth on the northern USAM in the World Oceans Database. Owing to high geographic and intra-annual BWT variability at <measure type="value"><num>250</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="mbsl">mbsl</measure></measure>, BWT of <measure type="value"><num>281</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> was assumed at these seeps. A higher BWT would reduce the volume of gas in a bubble. Lacking data on the temporal variation in seep emissions on the USAM, we assumed constant and continuous leakage for the methane emission calculation. The calculations were repeated for various values of bubble radii, number of emission sites per seep, bubble production rate and BWT conditions (Supplementary Table 3).</p>
  </text>
</tei>
