<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application version="0.6.2" ident="GROBID" when="2021-08-10T10:00+0000">
                    <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
        <p>Mean 1958-2007 Greenland Ice Sheet annual accumulation rate is <measure type="interval"><num type="base">337</num> ± <num type="range">48</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm/yr">mm/yr</measure></measure> water equivalent (w.e.) or <measure type="interval"><num type="base">591</num> ± <num type="range">83</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="Gt/yr">Gt/yr</measure></measure>. For example, Humboldt Main, North, and East were drilled <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> apart and have nearly the same mean accumulation rate (<measure type="list"><num>148</num>, <num>144</num> and <num>146</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm/yr">mm/yr</measure></measure> w.e., respectively) for their period of overlap (1929-1992).</p>
        <p>The 10 year average accumulation rate for IM is <measure type="interval"><num type="base">1028</num> ± <num type="range">568</num></measure>, decreasing to <measure type="interval"><num type="base">301</num> ± <num type="range">104</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g m^-2 yr^-1">g m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> for the 100 year average (Table 3). There is a prominent peak of IM accumulation in the top three intervals of SH3-1 that requires a scale adjustment compared to that used for the other five cores. The 10 year average accumulation rate for OM is <measure type="interval"><num type="base">462</num> ± <num type="range">97</num></measure> decreasing to <measure type="interval"><num type="base">267</num> ± <num type="range">46</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g m^-2 yr^-1">g m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> for the 100 year average (Table 3). The 10 year average OC burial rate is <measure type="interval"><num type="base">225</num> ± <num type="range">61</num></measure>, and decreases to <measure type="interval"><num type="base">123</num> ± <num type="range">19</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g m^-2 yr^-1">g m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> over the 100 year period. Variability for TN and TP accumulation rates shows the same general decline from the 10 year to 100 year averages, but both show extensive spatial variability at the 10 year level.</p>
        <p>The methane fraction (<measure type="value"><num>0.00268</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="kg kg-1">kg kg-1</measure></measure>) of the inflowing fluid is near the equilibrium solubility, and yields a methane influx of <measure type="value"><num>2.41 × 10-11</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="kg s^-1 m^-2">kg s-1 m-2</measure></measure>. The upward fluid velocity (~<measure type="value"><num>0.28</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm yr-1">mm a-1</measure></measure>) is not too different from that inferred by Davie and Buffett [2003a].</p>
        <p>In this study, the main boundary was placed at the onset of the Bùlling±Allerùd transition, which corresponds to the biozone 6a/5 boundary in the south Tyrrhenian cores (centred at 14.7 kyr bp).</p>
        <p>Central Chile (~35-38 °S), with the presence of an important upwelling center due to the predominance of southwesterly winds (Arcos and Wilson, 1984) and high primary productivity (maximum values of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="9.9">9.9</num>-<num atMost="19.9">19.9</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g m-2 d-1">g C m-2 d-1</measure></measure>) during the upwelling-favorable summer period (Bernal et al., 1989; Fossing et al., 1995; Dellarosa, 1998; Daneri et al., 2000).</p>
        <p>Other studies using Uranium series disequilibrium techniques (as in this study), which include mixing effects below the mixing layer, report SR between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.07">0.07</num> and <num atMost="0.11">0.11</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm yr^-1">cm yr-1</measure></measure> at shallow water depths (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num>-<num atMost="200">200</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>, ~12 °S) (Kim and Burnett, 1988).</p>
        <p>Two brief cooling events (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">500</num>±<num type="range">800</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure>) have been identified in the Uk37 SST record (C5 and C4, Fig. 3), respectively at 10.3 and 8.2 kyr bp. Similar cooling events have also been recognised in the Gulf of Cadiz Alboran Sea record (Cacho et al. 2000). This time interval is however characterised by strong modifications of the water column, since all the fossil organisms considered show changes in abundance. The pteropod association undergoes a period of crisis, with a dramatic decrease of shell deposition to the sea floor and the almost total disappearance of this group from the fossil record.</p>
        <p>Finally, based on comparisons between generally accepted values (see the foregoing discussion) for hydrate saturation (<measure type="value"><num atLeast="4">4</num> to <num atMost="7">7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of pore space) and fluid flux (~<measure type="value"><num>0.28</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm yr-1">mm a-1</measure></measure>) at the seafloor. The upward fluid velocity (~<measure type="value"><num>0.28</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm yr-1">mm a-1</measure></measure>) is not too different from that inferred by Davie and Buffett [2003a].</p>
        <p>Abyssal depth rates are functionally <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> at the time scale examined (~ <measure type="value"><num>10-4</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm yr^-1">cm year-1</measure></measure>) and increase one order of magnitude near the Mid-Atlantic Ridge and at the Galapagos Triple Junction.</p>
        <p>The 10 year accumulation rate for TP is <measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.58</num> ± <num type="range">0.25</num></measure> and <measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.20</num> ± <num type="range">0.08</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g m^-2 yr^-1">g m-2 yr-1</measure></measure> for the 100 year period (Table 3).</p>
        <p>Accumulation rates in southeast Greenland are found to exceed <measure type="value"><num>2000</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm/yr">mm/yr</measure></measure> w.e. and to dominate interannual variability in Greenland Ice Sheet total accumulated mass, representing <measure type="value"><num>31</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the whole.</p>
        <p>Reactive P mass accumulation rates (MARs) are ~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num>-<num atMost="110">110</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="µmol/cm2/ka">µmol/cm2/ka</measure></measure>, which is comparable to other open ocean locations but orders of magnitude lower than most upwelling settings.</p>
        <p>The temporal averaging required to attain spatially representative values is longer for low‐accumulation regions (i.e., <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> for Humboldt, ∼<measure type="value"><num>140</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm/yr">mm/yr</measure></measure> w.e.) and shorter for higher accumulation regions (i.e., <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> for NASA‐U, ∼<measure type="value"><num>330</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="mm/yr">mm/yr</measure></measure> w.e.)</p>
        <p>The flux of total detrital material calculated here was <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num>- to <num atMost="10">10</num></measure>-times larger than the eolian dust fluxes in SW Honshu and the south-central part of the Sea of Japan, which were estimated as less than <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="mg/cm2/year">mg/cm2/year</measure></measure> by observation [Osada et al. 2014] and analysis of sediment core precipitation summed up at each category (mm/day) observed at the Tsuruga observatory averaged from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1937">1937</num> to <num atMost="2012">2012</num></measure>.</p>
        <p>This database was compared with previously obtained results from central Peru (Callao). 210Pb activities decreased exponentially with core depth and proﬁles showed a deepening of the 210Pb in excess (unsupported) in the sediments from north to south (~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">6</num>-<num atMost="18">18</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> sediment depth off Peru and northern Chile vs. <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="8">8</num>-<num atMost="35">35</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> off central and southern Chile. An onshore-offshore decrease of surface activities was observed off central Peru whereas the reverse was true for surface activities along the Chilean margin. SRs increased from north (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.04">0.04</num>-<num atMost="0.17">0.17</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm yr-1">cm yr^-1</measure></measure>) to south (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.09">0.09</num>-<num atMost="0.29">0.29</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm yr-1">cm yr^-1</measure></measure>). Across the shelf, higher rates were observed at deeper sites, especially at those close to submarine canyons, except off central Peru, where SRs showed similar values through the slope area. Off northern Chile and central Peru, SRs seem to reﬂect the export of particles over the shelf and redistribution processes such as slumps and lateral transport. In contrast, SRs in central and southern Chile seem to be controlled by several additional factors that modulate the settling particles, such as onshore precipitation and river runoff. In addition, the more complex topography of the southern Chile margin allows for settling or winnowing areas.</p>
        <p>Differences between the stations off Mejillones (Fig. 4C) could be attributed to changes in the sediment composition or slumps that normally produce erratic 210Pbxs distribution proﬁles (Lewis et al., 2002). The shallow Station GEOB7104 shows anomalously high densities at the surface (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>-<num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>, <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1.2">1.2</num>-<num atLeast="0.9">0.9</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="g/cm3">g cm-3</measure></measure>) and lower values at depth (around <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="g/cm3">g cm-3</measure></measure>) (Fig. 2C) coincident with a slight increase in 210Pb and 226Ra activities (Fig. 4C). 226Ra tends to diminish with depth at both Stations GEOB7104 and GEOB7106, but a more erratic distribution is observed at GEOB7104.</p>
    </text>
</tei>
