<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="0.6.2" ident="GROBID" when="2021-08-17T12:00+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
    <p>Geochimicaet CosmochimicaActa, Vol. 60, No. 22, pp. 4313-4319. 1996 Copyright© 1996 ElsevierScienceLtd Printed in the USA. All rights reserved 0016-7037/96 $15.00 + .00  Pergamon  PII S0016-7037(96)00267-0  Sedimentation rate as determined by 226Ra activity in marine barite A. PAYTAN,1 W. S. MOORE,2 and M. KASTNERI ~Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093-0212, USA 2Department of Geological Sciences, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC 29208, USA  (Received July 23, 1996; accepted in revised form July 24, 1996)</p>
    <p>Abstract--In recently formed marine barite (BaSO4) separated from <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> equatorial Pacific cores 226Ra activity exceeds that of its parent 230Th by at least an order of magnitude, indicating radium uptake during barite precipitation. The decay of 226Ra with depth, in these samples, is exponential implying that no radium exchange with porewaters occurs after burial. Thus, barite behaves as a closed system below the sediment mixed layer. The absence of 226Ra exsactivity in barite samples older than ~<measure type="value"><num>8,000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure>, the lack of any detectable 228Th, 228Ra, and 224Ra in any of the barite samples analyzed, and the unaltered crystal size and habit with depth in the sediment, further support this conclusion. Hence, assuming that oceanic Ra/Ba ratio has not changed throughout the Holocene, the decay of unsupported 226Ra permits dating of marine barite and estimating sedimentation rates. Holocene sedimentation rates calculated using the decay of 226Raexs in barite are consistent with 14C and δ18O derived sedimentation rates of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num>-<num atMost="3">3</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure> for the same cores. The method could be extendible to carbonate-poor Holocene sediments.</p>
    <p>1. INTRODUCTION  1.1. General Background Barite in marine sediments records a variety of important oceanic processes and characteristics, i.e., paleoproductivity (Dymond et al., 1992; Schmitz, 1987; Shimmield et al., 1988), organic carbon export from the euphotic zone (Bishop, 1988; Dehairs et al., 1990, 1991), and seawater strontium isotope composition (Paytan et al., 1993). Little information is available on the fate of barite after burial, especially during early diagenesis. To evaluate its potential for short- and long-range geochemical paleoceanographic studies, it is important to determine the diagenetic behavior of barite. Already in the seventies it was recognized that the U-series radionuclides systematics in marine barite and associated sediments could enhance our understanding of the formation and early diagenesis of this phase (Church and Bernat, 1972; Borole and Somayajulu, 1977) and possibly provide the geochronology of the associated sediments (Lal and Somayajulu, 1975; Koide et al., 1976). Most seawater profiles are characterized by excess 226Ra, (t1/2 = 1600 y) over 230Th, due to the greater particle reactivity of thorium and the diffusion of radium into the water column from porewaters (Ivanovich and Harmon, 1992). In most marine sediments 230Th activity decreases with depth while 226Ra activity increases towards equilibrium with 230Th (Cochran, 1979; Kadko, 1980; Piggot and Urry, 1941), resulting in a subsurface maximum of 226Ra. The associated porewaters should have a similar 226Ra activity profile due to desorption from mineral surfaces and dissolution of sedimentary components. Thus, if barite crystals exchange radium with porewaters, or grow below the bioturbated zone in the sediment, the 226Ra/Ba ratio of sedimentary barite would also exhibit such a trend. Moreover, if barite continuously acquires barium and radium from porewaters, barite samples older than ~<measure type="value"><num>8,000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> would have excess 226Ra activities, from porewaters that contain 226Ra produced from 230Th in the sediments. Exponential decay of 226Ra in barite and no detection of 226Raexs activity in samples older than ~<measure type="value"><num>8000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure>, however, would suggest that barite behaves as a closed system with respect to radium.</p>
    <p>1.2. Previous Studies Earlier studies of radium, lead, thorium, and uranium in marine barite samples implied rapid exchange and remobilization of these elements (Church and Bernat, 1972; Borole and Somayajulu, 1977). Church and Bernat (1972) measured thorium and uranium concentrations in barite samples, reported 22STh/232Th activity ratios (AR) of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num>-<num atMost="21">21</num></measure> (with most values in the range of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num>-<num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> ) for barite from near core tops, and proposed that 228Ra in the barite was in rapid exchange equilibrium with porewaters. These data suggest that radium, and by implication also barium, reside in the barite for only about <measure type="value"><num>one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> before returning to the porewaters. Providing a mechanism for such rapid exchange was not forwarded and is problematic. Church and Bernat (1972) also reported 230Th/232Th AR in barite which are <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> times lower than the AR of the bulk sediment from which the barite was extracted. To explain this surprising result it was assumed the bulk sediment scavenged thorium from surface seawater where they postulate the 230Th/232Th AR is high, while the barite acquired thorium from deep or porewater where, they postulated, the ratio is low. We now know that the surface Pacific Ocean 230Th/232Th AR is low and the deep water ratio is high, just the reverse of what was postulated. Accordingly, their data imply that barite must preserve a surface ocean 230Th/232Th AR and is not in rapid exchange equilibrium with porewaters. Borole and Somayajulu (1977) measured 226Ra and 210Pb in barite samples separated from an eastern equatorial Pacific core with sedimentation rates of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num> - <num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure> from subsurface depth of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="42">42</num>-<num atMost="785">785</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>. Thus, all of the samples they analyzed were older than <measure type="value"><num>8,000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> and should not contain any residual excess 226Ra. They did, however, measure excess 226Ra in the barite samples and observed no decrease in 226Ra activity with depth in the core. Therefore, they concluded that the barite must be continuously growing in the sediment column. The Ra/Ba ratio in the porewaters and bottom waters in that area is, however, about a factor of <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> higher than the ratio in the barite and the distribution coefficient for radium in barite is close to <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> (Moore and Dymond, 1991 ); thus, the growth could not have been taking place in equilibrium with the porewater. Furthermore, no increase in barite crystal size nor change in crystal habit down-core were observed. They also recorded 210Pb/226Ra AR of only <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.04">0.04</num>-<num atMost="0.15">0.15</num></measure>; therefore, 222Rn escape from the barite crystals was speculated. Given the size of the crystals (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>-<num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure>), loss of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="85">85</num>-<num atMost="95">96</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the 222Rn is puzzling; when precipitated in the laboratory, barite does not emanate much 222Rn. The new radium and thorium data from equatorial Pacific marine barite samples, presented below, differ from the above and provide insights on marine barite formation and preservation and on the use of 226Ra decay in this phase as a dating tool of young marine sediments.</p>
    <p>2. EXPERIMENTAL METHODS Marine barite microcrystals from the upper <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> of <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> box cores from the central equatorial Pacific and from several older sediments were separated by sequential leaching with acetic acid, sodium hypochlorite, hydroxylamine hydrochloride, HNO3-HF mixture, and ashing, described in Paytan et al. (1993); all of the sediments are oxic. This procedure completely removes Fe-Mn oxyhydroxide coatings and preferentially removes radium relative to thorium from the barite surfaces, but does not affect the radium in the barite structure. The 226Ra activities of these barites and 226Ra and 210Pb activities of the bulk sediment were measured by γ-ray spectrometry, using an intrinsic germanium detector with a <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> diameter well (Moore, 1984). The activities of other gamma emitters, specifically, 228Th, 228Ra, and 224Ra, were monitored; no activities of these nuclides were detected above background level for any of the barite samples measured. The 230Th, 232Th, and uranium isotopes activities in barite samples were measured by dissolution in the presence of a 232U-228Th isotope dilution spike and alpha spectrometry (Rubin, 1991 ). The errors reported in Table 1 are the 2σ counting variance. To examine the possibility of adsorption of radium and thorium on barite surfaces from the bulk sediment during the separation procedure, 228Ra and 229Th spikes were added to each step of the barite separation treatment of selected samples. About <measure type="list"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> of the Th and <num>0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the radium spikes were adsorbed onto the cleaned barite surfaces. The activity of the adsorbed fraction of radium is insignificant relative to the total radium activity in barite crystals younger than <measure type="value"><num>8,000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure>, in the cores analyzed in this work. Therefore, corrections for these adsorbed activities were not made; they do not significantly change the results obtained in this work.</p>
    <p>3. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION  3.1. 226Ra Activity in Marine Barite and Associated Sediments The 226Ra and 230Th activities of barite samples, the depth of the sediment from which they were extracted, and the 14C ages of these sediments are given in Table 1 a and b. The uranium concentrations in the samples were less than <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="ppm">ppm</measure></measure>, negligible in comparison to thorium, indicating that essentially all the 230Th in the barite crystals is unsupported.</p>
    <p>230Th/232Th AR ranged between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num> and <num atMost="190">190</num></measure>, with a mean of about <measure type="value"><num>100</num></measure>, which is consistent with the ratio in the bulk sediments in this area (R. F. Anderson, pers. commun.). Considering the high counting error associated with the very low 232Th activities and small sample size the range of values is probably experimental. The 226Ra activities versus depth of marine barite from the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> equatorial Pacific cores are shown in Fig. 1. Bulk sediment 226Ra activities were also measured and compared with bulk sediment 230Thoxs and 210Pbexs activities (Table 1c; Fig. 2). The 226Ra activity of barite is considerably higher than that of the bulk sediment (Fig. 1). Since barite comprises <measure type="value"><num>0.25</num></measure> wt% of these sediments, it accounts for up to <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the bulk sediment 226Ra activity. The exponential decrease of Z26Ra in barite with depth in the upper <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> of the cores suggests that barite behaves as a closed system with respect to radium and is not affected by exchange or recrystallization (Fig. 1). It is unlikely that such a curve would be produced by precipitation of barite or exchange of barium and radium in the barite crystals with the porewater because the porewater barium concentrations in these cores remain relatively constant below a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">centimeters</measure></measure> depth (Paytan and Kastner, 1996). Lack of any detectable 228Th, 228Ra, and 224Ra activities in any of the barite samples analyzed also suggest that no or insignificant barite growth is occurring in the sediment below the bioturbated zone. This conclusion is supported by the similar morphology of the crystals to those observed in the water column (Bishop, 1988; Dehairs et al., 1980) and the strontium isotope composition of previously analyzed barite samples (Paytan et al., 1993). The absence of any excess 226Ra activity in barite from sediments older than - <measure type="value"><num>8,000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> further reinforces this conclusion (PC72 and ODP samples, Table 1b). 222Rn (decay product of 226Ra) emanation from the barite crystals was also measured in order to verify the closed-system behavior. The emanation coefficient (radon emerging from mineral grains/radon generated in the mineral by decay of radium) was found to be <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. This is equal to the emanation due to recoil of radon from a thin surficial layer of radium in grains which are ~ <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> in size (Rama and Moore, 1990), and indicates no 222Rn escape from the barite crystals, as expected from a closed-system behavior. The 226Ra/Ba ratio in barite separated from sediments in the mixed layer is about <measure type="value"><num>0.3</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="dpm/µmol">dpm/µmol</measure></measure>. This ratio is lower than the 226Ra/Ba ratio of about <measure type="value"><num>1.2</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="dpm/µmol">dpm/µmol</measure></measure> of particulate matter recovered from sediment traps in this area (Moore and Dymond, 1991 ). Assuming most of the barium and radium in the particulate matter resides in barite (Moore and Dymond, 1991 ), the lower ratio in the crystals is consistent with the decay of 226Ra during the residence time of the sediment in the mixed-layer, which is ~<measure type="value"><num>3000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> based on 14C data by DeMaster and Pope (1994). These data suggest that barite is forming in the water column. But, assuming that the concentration in the upper centimeters of the porewater radium is equal to that of the bottom water, the 226Ra/ Ba ratio of porewaters from the upper <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> of the sediment in this area would be <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="dpm/µmol">dpm/µmol</measure></measure> (Paytan, 1995) (which is clearly a minimum value); thus, an early-diagenetic barite formation, close to the sediment water interface where porewaters are supersaturated with respect to barite, cannot be ruled out. In either case the 226Ra activity data indicate that barite once formed (in the water column and/or at the sediment water interface) remains a closed system with respect to radium. Hence, marine barite is a suitable phase for geochemical paleoceanographic studies and the decay of 226Ra in these barite samples can be used for geochronology. These results for radium and thorium in marine barite differ significantly from those of Church and Bernat (1972) and Borole and Somayajulu (1977) discussed above. We suspect that the milder sequential leaching procedure they used did not remove all detrital material and oxyhydroxide coatings from the barite; the X-ray analysis they used to confirm the sample purity is only semiquantitative. These impurities probably had a 230Th/232Th AR close to <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> and 228Th, which would have lowered the apparent 230Th/232Th AR and produced an apparent high 228Th/232Th AR in the barite relative to the bulk sediment. The reported new data are from samples with considerably higher barite/detritus ratios, and a more extreme HF leach step was used to ensure the removal of detrital components. In addition, special precautions were taken to thoroughly leach the marine barite crystals surface coatings of Fe-Mn oxyhydroxides, which are known to adsorb radium and thorium, as described in Paytan (1995).</p>
    <p>Sedimentation rates of <measure type="value"><num>3.6</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr^-1">cm/kyr</measure></measure> at the equator and <measure type="value"><num>2.7</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure> at 2°N are derived from the slope of the logarithm of 226Ra (dpm/gm) in barite versus depth below the bioturbation zone (Fig. 3, empty symbols). These are maximum sedimentation rates because most likely a larger fraction of the measured radium in the older samples is produced by 230Th in the barite (supported 226Ra). It is unclear where the thorium resides in the barite crystals but it is most likely adsorbed onto the crystal surfaces from the surrounding porewater; the similar 230Th/232Th activity ratios determined in the bulk sediment support this conclusion. For comparison, the unsupported ZZ6Ra(226Raexs) in the barite crystals was also calculated (Table 1a). This calculation assumes that all the barite is authigenic and that the 226Ra in barite is incorporated from the water column or at the sediment-water interface, while the thorium is adsorbed onto the barite surfaces from the porewater. With time 230Th generates supported 226Ra as the initial excess 226Ra decays. The unsupported 226Rae×s is then given by 226Ratotal - 226Rasup. = 226Raexs. Thus, the excess 226Ra (N02e-λ2t) was calculated using the following equation:</p>
    <p>in which the subscript 1 refers to the parent 230Th and the subscript 2 refers to the daughter 226Ra; N stands for the total number of atoms of the isotope measured (dpm/λ); λ is the decay constant of the isotope, t is the age of the sample, and N0 is the initial number of atoms of the corresponding isotope, at zero age. 226Ra has a half-life of <measure type="value"><num>1600</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> years and 230Th has a half-life of <measure type="value"><num>75,200</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure>. The initial 230Th activity is calculated from the measured 230Thactivity of each sample and the age of the sample using: N01 = N1/-λ1t The 230Th produced 226Ra was calculated from the 14C age of the sample (DeMaster and Pope, 1994). This method of calculating the excess 226Ra assumes that the ingrown radium is not lost to porewaters through alpha recoil and/or during the leaching. Also, because postdepositional thorium adsorption is a continuos process and the chemical treatment preferentially removes radium and does not completely remove thorium from surfaces, as indicated by the apparent Ra deficiency in the older samples (Table 1b), this method over-corrects for Th-supported radium and the 226Raexs activities are minimum values. The calculated 226Raexsin the barite crystals are given in Table 1a, and the calculated sedimentation rates derived from the logarithm of 226Raexs (dpm/gm) in barite versus depth below the bioturbation zone (Fig. 3, full symbols) are <measure type="value"><num>3.0</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure> at the equator and <measure type="value"><num>2.4</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure> at 2°N. The sedimentation rates calculated with or without correction for supported radium are similar and only slightly higher than 14C based estimates (<measure type="list"><num>2.3</num> and <num>2.1</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure>, respectively, DeMaster and Pope, 1994), and of the same order as δ18O derived sedimentation rates ( ~ <measure type="value"><num>3.2</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure>, Murray et al., 1995). Such sedimentation rates are quite typical for the equatorial Pacific Ocean and are much higher than those calculated from the slope of the logarithm of excess 230Th in bulk sediment versus depth (<measure type="list"><num>0.26</num> and <num>0.23</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm/kyr">cm/kyr</measure></measure>, respectively), suggesting that 230Th accumulation in these sediments is not constant with time and might be influenced by other processes such as carbonate dissolution (Marcantonio et al., 1995). Sediments in the mixed layer are deficient in 226Rarelative to 230Th due to thorium scavenging from the water column and radium loss from the bioturbated zone, and the deficiency decreases with depth. Trap samples from 1°N, 139°W (MANOP site C) have a bulk 226Ra/230Th activity ratio of &gt;<measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> (W. S. Moore, unpubl, data). The 226Ra/230Th activity ratio in the sediment mixed layer is <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num></measure>, in agreement with radium loss to the water column. The bioturbation coefficients (Db) , representing the intensity of sediment mixing, were calculated using the bulk sediment 210Pbexs data in the mixed layer and the relation Db = λz2/[ln(C0/Cz)]2, where C0 and Cz are the excess 210Pb activities at depths of <measure type="value"><num>0</num> and z <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>, and λ is the 210Pb decay constant as described in Smith et al. (1993). Results yield coefficients of <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="cm2/yr">cm2/yr</measure></measure> for the equator and <measure type="value"><num>0.06</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="cm2/yr">cm2/yr</measure></measure> at 2°N. Employing an equation that relates the 210Pbexs profile, bioturbation coefficient, and the sedimentation rate in a core (DeMaster and Cochran, 1982), a good fit to the data in the equator core was obtained using a sedimentation rate of <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr-1">cm kyr-1</measure></measure>, which is consistent with the sedimentation rate calculated using 226Ra decay in barite.</p>
    <p>4. CONCLUSIONS Marine barite in oxic pelagic sediments behaves as a closed system with respect to radium and thus is a suitable authigenic marine phase for chemical paleoceanographic studies. In Holocene sediments &lt; <measure type="value"><num>8000</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> old the decay of excess 226Ra in barite provides reliable sedimentation rates, and therefore can be utilized for dating carbonate poor sediments.</p>
  </text>
</tei>
