<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="0.6.2" ident="GROBID" when="2021-08-17T12:00+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
    <p>Available online at www.sciencedirect.com  Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta 75 (2011) 7257-7276 www.elsevier.com/locate/gca  Early diagenesis of redox-sensitive trace metals in the Peru upwelling area - response to ENSO-related oxygen ﬂuctuations in the water column Florian Scholz, Christian Hensen, Anna Noﬀke, Anne Rohde, Volker Liebetrau, Klaus Wallmann Leibniz Institute of Marine Sciences, IFM-GEOMAR, Marine Biogeochemistry, Wischhofstraße 1-3, D-24148 Kiel, Germany Received 11 April 2011; accepted in revised form 2 August 2011; available online 9 August 2011</p>
    <p>Abstract Pore water and solid phase data for redox-sensitive metals (Mn, Fe, V, Mo and U) were collected on a transect across the Peru upwelling area (11°S) at water depths between <measure type="interval"><num atLest="78">78</num> and <num atMost="2025">2025</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> and bottom water oxygen concentrations ranging from ~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num> to <num atMost="93">93</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>. By comparing authigenic mass accumulation rates and diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes, we evaluate the respective mechanisms of trace metal accumulation, retention and remobilization across the oxygen minimum zone (OMZ) and with respect to oxygen ﬂuctuations in the water column related to the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO). Sediments within the permanent OMZ are characterized by diﬀusive uptake and authigenic ﬁxation of U, V and Mo as well as diﬀusive loss of Mn and Fe across the benthic boundary. Some of the dissolved Mn and Fe in the water column reprecipitate at the oxycline and shuttle particle-reactive trace metals to the sediment surface at the lower and upper boundary of the OMZ. At the lower boundary, pore waters are not suﬃciently sulﬁdic as to enable an eﬃcient authigenic V and Mo ﬁxation. As a consequence, sediments below the OMZ are preferentially enriched in U which is delivered via both in situ precipitation and lateral supply of U-rich phosphorites from further upslope. Trace metal cycling on the Peruvian shelf is strongly aﬀected by ENSO-related oxygen ﬂuctuations in bottom water. During periods of shelf oxygenation, surface sediments receive particulate V and Mo with metal (oxyhydr)oxides that derive from both terrigenous sources and precipitation at the retreating oxycline. After the recurrence of anoxic conditions, metal (oxyhydr)oxides are reductively dissolved and the hereby liberated V and Mo are authigenically removed. This alternation between supply of particle-reactive trace metals during oxic periods and ﬁxation during anoxic periods leads to a preferential accumulation of V and Mo compared to U on the Peruvian shelf. The decoupling of V, Mo and U accumulation is further accentuated by the varying susceptibility to re-oxidation of the diﬀerent authigenic metal phases. While authigenic U and V are readily re-oxidized and recycled during periods of shelf oxygenation, the sequestration of Mo by authigenic pyrite is favored by the transient occurrence of oxidizing conditions. Our ﬁndings reveal that redox-sensitive trace metals respond in speciﬁc manner to short-term oxygen ﬂuctuations in the water column. The relative enrichment patterns identiﬁed might be useful for the reconstruction of past OMZ extension and large-scale redox oscillations in the geological record.  * Corresponding author. Tel.: +49 431 600 2562; fax: +49 431 6002928. E-mail address: fscholz@ifm-geomar.de (F. Scholz).  0016-7037/$ - see front matter Ó 2011 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved. doi:10.1016/j.gca.2011.08.007</p>
    <p>1. INTRODUCTION 1.1. Scientiﬁc conception It is generally accepted that the accumulation of redoxsensitive metals in marine sediments is primarily controlled by bottom water oxygen concentrations classifying the respective environment into oxic (&gt;<measure type="value"><num>63</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> O2), hypoxic (&lt;<measure type="value"><num>63</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> O2), anoxic (<measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> O2) or anoxic-sulﬁdic (<measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> O2, &gt;<measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> H2S) (classiﬁcation after Middelburg and Levin, 2009). The ﬁxation or liberation of metals is mostly due to the diﬀering solubility of oxidized and reduced species. In other words, interaction between sediment pore waters and minerals is the ultimate reason for most trace metal enrichments or depletions with respect to the detrital background. Much of our knowledge on the behavior of redoxsensitive metals in oceanic pore waters has been deduced at oxic and hypoxic sites in the N Atlantic and N Paciﬁc margins (e.g. Klinkhammer and Palmer, 1991; Shaw et al., 1994; Zheng et al., 2000; Chaillou et al., 2002; Zheng et al., 2002a; McManus et al., 2005; Morford et al., 2005) as well as in anoxic-sulﬁdic basins with restricted water column circulation such as the Cariaco Trench and the Black Sea (e.g. Anderson et al., 1989a,b; Barnes and Cochran, 1990; Emerson and Huested, 1991). To date, no systematic studies on the pore water chemistry of trace metals have been carried out in the pronounced eastern boundary oxygen minimum zones (OMZs) of the southern Paciﬁc and Atlantic. This is a remarkable gap, considering that these regions strongly diﬀer from the aforementioned systems regarding their water column circulation pattern and/or the extent of detrital input, primary productivity and oxygen depletion. The Peru upwelling system is of additional interest, since it is strongly aﬀected by oceanographic large-scale perturbations related to the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO). Understanding the inﬂuence of ENSO-related annual and interannual oscillations in bottom water redox conditions on trace metal cycling is not possible based on solid phase geochemical data alone, but necessitates a thorough examination of pore water proﬁles. The trace metals studied here, V, Mo and U, are widely used as paleo-redox indicators (e.g. Brumsack, 2006; Tribovillard et al., 2006; Algeo and Tribovillard, 2009). A detailed understanding of how they respond to transient re-oxidation and redox oscillations is an important prerequisite to identify similar environmental conditions in the geological record. Moreover, climate change and anthropogenically induced eutrophication will lead to an increasing occurrence of seasonal or perennial shelf hypoxia in the coming decades (Diaz, 2001; Diaz and Rosenberg, 2008; Stramma et al., 2008). Trace element cycling in the dynamic Peruvian OMZ may therefore serve as a paradigm for future scenarios in which high-amplitude oxygen ﬂuctuations such as those related to ENSO will occur more frequently. In this article we discuss sediment and pore water data for V, Mo, U and related redox species (Mn, Fe, H2S) that were collected on a transect across the Peruvian OMZ at 11°S. The comparison of authigenic mass accumulation rates and diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes enables a quantitative evaluation of the respective mechanisms of trace metal accumulation and retention or remobilization. Finally, we discuss implications for the use of U-Mo systematics as a paleo-proxy for oxygen ﬂuctuations in bottom water and combine our results in a conceptual model, illustrating the lateral and temporal variability of V, Mo and U diagenesis across the Peru upwelling area.</p>
    <p>1.2. Marine geochemistry of vanadium, molybdenum and uranium  The three trace metals studied here share many chemical characteristics giving rise to their joint enrichment in oxygen-deﬁcient sediment facies. There are, however, subtle differences in their diagenetic behaviors that make this suite of elements particularly interesting for studies on redox oscillations. While Mo and U exhibit a conservative behavior in the ocean (residence time of Mo: ~<measure type="value"><num>800</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="kyr">kyr</measure></measure>, U: ~<measure type="value"><num>400</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="kyr">kyr</measure></measure>), a slight surface depletion is observed for V (residence time of V: ~<measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="kyr">kyr</measure></measure>). In oxic seawater, their major dissolved species are oxyanions of V(V) (vanadate, HVO2- 4 ), Mo(VI) (molyb) and U(VI) (uranyl carbonate, UO2(CO3)4- date, MoO2- 3) Vanadate readily adsorbs to Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides in the water column and molybdate is also well known for its strong aﬃnity to particulate Mn (oxyhydr)oxides in oxic settings (Chan and Riley, 1966a,b; Shimmield and Price, 1986; Wehrli and Stumm, 1989; Barling and Anbar, 2004). Moreover, in a recent isotope geochemical study Goldberg et al. (2009) underscored the importance of Fe (oxyhydr)oxides as a solid carrier for Mo to the sediment surface. Upon reductive dissolution of Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides in the surface sediment, V and Mo oxyanions are released into the pore water and either diﬀuse back into the water column or become trapped by authigenic phases within the sediments (Shaw et al., 1990; Emerson and Huested, 1991; Morford et al., 2005). In reducing (pore) waters V(V) is stepwise reduced to V(IV) and, if free H2S is present, to V(III) (Wehrli and Stumm, 1989; Wanty and Goldhaber, 1992). Most of the reduced V species are prone to removal from the dissolved phase, through surface adsorption of vanadyl (VO2+) or organic V(IV) complexes, formation of insoluble V(III) oxides or hydroxides and incorporation of V(III) in refractory organic compounds (e.g. porphyrins) or authigenic clay minerals (Breit and Wanty, 1991; Wanty and Goldhaber, 1992; Calvert and Pedersen, 1993). Molybdate undergoes successive sulﬁdation at H2S concentrations above a critical threshold level (~<measure type="value"><num>0.1</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>; Zheng et al., 2000) leading to the formation of thiomolybdates (MoOx S2- 4-x , 1 &lt; x &lt; 4) (Helz et al., 1996; Erickson and Helz, 2000). Because of the strong aﬃnity of thiomolybdates to reactive surfaces, Mo is readily scavenged in anoxic-sulﬁdic environments by forming bonds with metal-rich particles (e.g. less reactive Fe oxides), Fe sulﬁdes and sulfur-rich organic molecules (Huerta-Diaz and Morse, 1992; Helz et al., 1996; Bostick et al., 2003; Tribovillard et al., 2004; Vorlicek et al., 2004). If Mo (and presumably also V) is removed from pore water at or directly below the sediment surface, a direct diﬀusive ﬂux across the benthic boundary may be established (Zheng et al., 2000). Uranyl carbonate does not adsorb to Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides or any other inorganic particles in the water column. In reducing pore water, U(VI) is reduced to U(IV), a process that is typically observed in the Fe reduction zone (Barnes and Cochran, 1990, 1991; Klinkhammer and Palmer, 1991; Zheng et al., 2002a). Since U reduction does not occur in the water column of anoxic basins (Anderson et al., 1989a,b), it is believed to be catalyzed by reactive mineral surfaces and, most notably, enzymes produced by Fe and possibly sulfate reducing bacteria (Lovley et al., 1991; Lovley and Phillips, 1992; Lovley et al., 1993; Liger et al., 1999; Zheng et al., 2002a; Suzuki et al., 2005). Reduced U is removed from the pore water through adsorption or precipitation of U oxides (mainly uraninite, UO2). The resulting concentration gradient promotes a downward diﬀusive ﬂux of U across the benthic boundary. A variety of interlinked factors have been proposed to control the magnitude of this ﬂux, including the bottom water oxygen concentration, the sinking rate of organic carbon and the combined rates of Fe and sulfate reduction (Zheng et al., 2002a; McManus et al., 2005, 2006; Morford et al., 2009a). It is generally agreed that most of the U in anoxic sediments is delivered by diﬀusion across the sediment-bottom water interface (McManus et al., 2005; Morford et al., 2009a). Notwithstanding, a few studies have revealed that a signiﬁcant portion of the U buried in sediments beneath an anoxic water column may be delivered as bioauthigenic U (or particulate non-lithogenic U, PNU) which had originally formed in the photic zone (Anderson et al., 1989a; Zheng et al., 2002a,b). At oxic sites, this organically bound U is completely regenerated during its transit through the water column (Anderson, 1982). According to Zheng et al. (2002b), however, preservation of the bioauthigenic U may reach <measure type="value"><num>100</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> if water column oxygen concentrations drop below <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>. Once accumulated, trace metals may be re-mobilized if they become temporarily exposed to more oxidizing conditions, e.g. due to re-suspension and bioturbation or bioirrigation. Therefore, sediments underlying oxic bottom water retain only a small fraction of the originally delivered metals (Zheng et al., 2002a; Morford et al., 2009a,b). Because of their diﬀerent sources (particulate versus diﬀusive) or diagenetic sinks (oxides, sulﬁdes, association with organic molecules), V, Mo and U are anticipated to respond in different manner to lateral and temporal changes in bottom water oxygenation.    2. STUDY AREA  The coastal area oﬀ Peru (Fig. 1) is characterized by southeasterly alongshore winds driven by the Paciﬁc Subtropical Anticyclone throughout most of the year. These atmospheric conditions promote strong oﬀshore Ekman transport of surface waters within the Peru coastal current and upwelling of subsurface waters from the poleward ﬂowing Peru undercurrent (Strub and Montecino, 1998). The upwelled water is oxygen-depleted and rich in nutrients thus enabling a high primary productivity in the photic zone (~<measure type="value"><num>3.6</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g m-2 d-1">g m-2 d-1</measure></measure>; Pennington et al., 2006). Intense degradation of organic matter leads to a near-complete drawdown of dissolved oxygen in the water column. As a result, an OMZ is established above the Peruvian shelf and upper slope extending roughly from &lt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num> to <num atMost="700">700</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth (oxycline of <measure type="value"><num>22</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> deﬁned by Fuenzalida et al. (2009). While the lower boundary of the OMZ is relatively stable, the upper boundary underlies considerable ﬂuctuations that are mainly tied to the passage of coastal trapped waves (Gutiérrez et al., 2008). These emerge from equatorial Kelvin waves in the equatorial East Paciﬁc and occur more frequently during positive ENSO periods (Brink, 1982; Hormazabal et al., 2001; Pizarro et al., 2001). The propagation of coastal trapped waves is accompanied by a signiﬁcant thermocline and oxycline deepening, shifting the upper boundary of the OMZ by <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth or more (Gutiérrez et al., 2008). Most intense oxygenation events have been observed during the El Niño periods of 1982/1983 and 1997/1998 during which the upper boundary of the OMZ deepened to almost <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (Levin et al., 2002; Fuenzalida et al., 2009). Seasonal ﬂuctuations are of inferior importance although a maximum in wind speed and coastal upwelling has been reported for austral winter and spring (Scheidegger and Krissek, 1983; Strub and Montecino, 1998; Soto-Mardones et al., 2004). Oﬀshore Peru between 10° and 14°S, upwelling-inﬂuenced sediments accumulate in a coastal mud lens extending from the depth of the wave base to <measure type="value"><num>500</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth on the upper slope. The anomalously ﬁne grained sediments in this area consist of a mixture of terrigenous matter with ~<measure type="value"><num>18</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="wt.%">wt.%</measure></measure> of biogenic silica and organic mater contents of up to <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="wt.%">wt.%</measure></measure> (Scheidegger and Krissek, 1983). Below the mud lens and up to a water depth of &gt;<measure type="value"><num>1500</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>, strong bottom currents cause reworking and winnowing of sediments leading to a much coarser grain size distribution and lower contents of organic carbon. Furthermore, the high energy regime prevailing mid-slope favors the formation and accumulation of phosphorite crusts and nodules (Reimers and Suess, 1983; Glenn and Arthur, 1988).</p>
    <p>3. MATERIALS AND METHODS 3.1. Sampling and onboard analytics Fourteen sediment cores were retrieved on a transect along 11°S during the M77-1 and M77-2 cruises of RV Meteor that took place from November 22nd to December 21st of 2008 (Fig. 1). The geographical position and water column properties of all sampling stations are summarized in Table 1. Hydrographic data and oxygen concentrations in the water column were obtained by deploying a CTD/rosette equipped with an oxygen sensor. Sediment samples were retrieved using a video-guided multiple corer (MUC) equipped with PVC liners with an inner diameter of <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>. After recovery, MUCs with an undisturbed sediment/bottom water interface were plugged and immediately carried into a cooling lab which was kept at in situ (i.e. seaﬂoor) temperature. The bottom water was siphoned with a plastic tube and ﬁltered through cellulose acetate syringe ﬁlters. Sediment subsampling was performed under inert atmosphere in an argon-ﬂushed glove bag. The glove bag was ﬁlled and emptied repeatedly in order to remove any oxygen prior to sampling. The MUCs were cut into <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>-<num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> thick slices with the highest resolution at the surface and the pore water was separated from the sediment by centrifuging for 20 min at 4500 rpm. The centrifuge vials were then transferred into a second glove bag where the supernatant water was ﬁltered through cellulose acetate syringe ﬁlters. A small pore water aliquot was acidiﬁed in the glove bag with ascorbic acid for onboard Fe analyses. Concentrations of ferrous Fe and H2S were determined shortly after pore water recovery by standard spectrophotometric techniques (Stookey, 1970; Grasshoﬀ et al., 2002). Subsamples for metal analyses were stored in acid-cleaned LDPE vials and acidiﬁed with concentrated HNO3 (supra pure). The residual sediments in centrifuge vials were frozen and stored for total digestions after the cruise. An additional sediment aliquot was taken from a parallel MUC and stored in air tight plastic cups for the determination of water content and porosity as well as for total organic carbon (TOC) and total sulfur (TS) analyses. Two of the sediment cores discussed in this article were obtained from benthic lander deployments (Biogeochemical Observatory - BIGO; Sommer et al., 2006). These cores were processed in the same way as described above for MUCs. 3.2. Chemical analyses The TOC and TS content of freeze-dried and ground sediment samples was determined by ﬂash combustion in a Carbo Erba Element Analyzer (NA1500) with an analytical precision of about <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for replicate analyses. For total metal concentrations, 100 mg of freeze dried and ground sediment sample were digested in HF (<measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, supra pure), HNO3 (<measure type="value"><num>65</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, supra pure) and HClO4 (<measure type="value"><num>60</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, p.a.). The accuracy of the digestion procedure was monitored by including method blanks and the reference standards SDO-1 (Devonian Ohio Shale, USGS; Govindaraju, 1994), MESS-3 (Marine Sediment Reference Material, Canadian Research Council) as well as the in-house standard OMZ-1. Average values of replicate digestions were generally well within the recommended ranges with relative standard deviations (RSD) being &lt;<measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for Al, Mn and Fe and &lt;<measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for V, Mo and U (n = 9). The analysis of Mn, Fe and Al in digestion solutions was carried out using an inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometer (ICP-OES, VARIAN 720-ES). Trace metal concentrations (V, Mo and U) in digestion solutions as well as the metal concentration (Mn, Fe, V, Mo and U) of all bottom and pore water samples were measured by inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS, Agilent Technologies 7500 Series) in H2 reaction (Fe) or He collision (other elements) mode. Samples were diluted 20-fold with <measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> HNO3 (sub-boiled, distilled) prior to analysis. Calibration standards for bottom and pore water analyses were prepared with an appropriate volume of artiﬁcial seawater in order to adjust them to the sample matrix. Samples and standards were spiked with an internal standard solution (Sc, Y and In) in order to correct for instrumental mass bias. Despite internal standardization, an instrumental drift was observed for U. Therefore, each block of four samples was bracketed with a pair of an appropriate calibration standard and a certiﬁed reference standard (CASS-5, Nearshore Seawater; Canadian Research Council) was measured in the middle of each block. The drift was corrected for by calculating a drift factor from the change in U concentration measured for the calibration standard and the goodness of the correction was monitored by comparing the concentration measured for the reference standard with the certiﬁed value. Accuracies for replicate analyses of CASS-5 are summarized in Table 2. Our results for Mn and V are in good agreement with the certiﬁed ranges and precision values based on replicate measurement of CASS-5 and pore water samples are &lt;<measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> RSD for all elements. CASS-5 is not certiﬁed for Mo and U but the deviation of our average values from the recommended values are &lt;<measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> which is a typical uncertainty for trace metals in reference standards. Concentrations of Fe in CASS-5 are below the detection limit of our method. However, the ICPMS results for total Fe are mostly in good agreement with the ferrous Fe data obtained onboard by spectrophotometry. Deviations &gt;<measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> occur mainly at the OMZ boundaries and are therefore attributed to higher concentrations of ferric Fe. Diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes for Fe reported in later sections and all pore water Fe plots are based on the onboard Fe data.</p>
    <p>3.3. Quantiﬁcation of trace metal accumulation Sediment mass accumulation rates (MARs; in g cm-2 kyr-1) were calculated from sedimentation rate (SR; in cm kyr-1), dry bulk density (qdry; in g cm-3) and the average porosity at the lower core end (ρ_inf ): MAR = ρdry (1 - /1 )SR Sedimentation rates were obtained for selected cores by measuring gamma-ray excess 210Pb activities and modeling the resulting proﬁles as described in Meysman et al. (2005). Porosity values were determined from the water loss after freeze drying and dry bulk density was approximated from TOC concentrations using an empirical relationship that is based on data for Peru upwelling sediments from Böning et al. (2004). Multiplying the MAR with the average authigenic metal concentration ([Me]auth) yields the authigenic metal MAR. The authigenic metal concentration, which is deﬁned as the diﬀerence between the total metal concentration ([Me]tot) and the detrital background ([Me]detr), was calculated as follows:  Böning et al. (2004) demonstrated that the chemical composition of andesite is an appropriate representation of the detrital background on the Peruvian margin. Average metal/Al ratios for andesite rocks in the Andean Arc were derived from the GEOROC data base of the MaxPlanck Institute for Chemistry, Mainz, Germany (Sarbas and Nohl, 2009). A comparison between the ratios of andesite in the Andean Arc, Post-Archaean Australian average shale and average upper continental crust is provided in Table 3. Diﬀusive ﬂuxes of metals across the benthic boundary were calculated by Fick’s ﬁrst law of diﬀusion:  where d[C]/dx denotes the concentration diﬀerence between the bottom water and the uppermost pore water sample divided by the depth of the uppermost pore water sample (<measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>). By deﬁnition, positive ﬂuxes are directed into the sediment. Diﬀusion coeﬃcients for metal ions in seawater (Dsw) were adjusted to in situ temperature and pressure using the Stokes-Einstein equation. Diﬀusion coeﬃcients for sediments (Dsed) were calculated as:  and tortuosity (h2) was derived from porosity using the following relationship from Boudreau (1996):   4. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION 4.1. Sediment redox state and diagenetic zoning At the time of sampling, the Peruvian margin was overlain by a pronounced OMZ with the core (O2 &lt; <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>) ranging roughly from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num>-<num atMost="500">500</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth (Fig. 2). Pore water proﬁles of Mn, Fe, H2S, U, V and Mo are shown in Fig. 3. The stations are ordered according to increasing water depth and combined in 4 subpanels based on similarities in the shape of their pore water proﬁles. These subpanels and the corresponding areas on the margin (i.e. water column and sediments) will be referred to as zone I (shallowest stations) to zone IV (stations below ~<measure type="value"><num>600</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth) in the following sections. Fig. 2 shows exemplary oxygen proﬁles in the water column for each of the four zones. The only zone where bottom water oxygen concentrations rose above a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> during the sampling campaign is zone IV. Highest dissolved Mn and Fe concentrations (up to <measure type="value"><num>190</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> of Mn and <measure type="value"><num>35</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> of Fe) are observed in zone I where pore water proﬁles of Mn and Fe display pronounced maxima close to the sediment/bottom water interface. Lower concentrations and less steep concentration-depth gradients prevail in zones II and III. In zone IV, the uppermost <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> of the sediments show again a surface maximum in Mn whereas the Fe concentrations drop to zero. Diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes for Mn, Fe, U, V and Mo are shown in Table 4 and plotted against water depth in Fig. 4. Highest ﬂux values for both Mn and Fe are observed in the shallowest core in zone I (BIGO-05). The Mn ﬂuxes decrease steadily with increasing water depth to values close to zero in MUC21 (465 m) and increase again below. The Fe ﬂuxes are more randomly distributed in zones II and III and are zero in zone IV. The Mn and Fe ﬂux across the benthic boundary is driven by reductive dissolution of reactive Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides in the surface sediments (Froelich et al., 1979; Burdige, 1993; Pakhomova et al., 2007). Notwithstanding, most of the Mn which is delivered to the OMZ is already reduced in the water column (cp. Böning et al., 2004). This is illustrated by low pore water Mn concentrations and diffusive ﬂuxes compared to other continental margin settings (Figs. 3 and 4; cp. Pakhomova et al., 2007 and references therein), little downcore variability of Mn/Al in the sediments (see Supplementary EA-Table 1 in the Electronic Annex) and a strong depletion of Mn with respect to the detrital background in sediments on the entire continental margin (Fig. 5 and Böning et al., 2004). Some Fe reduction might occur in the water column as well. However, the benthic Fe ﬂuxes reported here fall in the upper range of values reported for a wide range of environments (Severmann et al., 2010; Noﬀke et al., 2011), suggesting that the surface sediments are the principal locus of Fe reduction in the Peruvian OMZ. A similar conclusion has been drawn by Bruland et al. (2005) based on the distribution of dissolved ferrous Fe in the water column. The magnitude of the diﬀusive Fe ﬂux across the sediment/bottom water interface is controlled by both the bottom water oxygen concentrations and the availability of reactive Fe (Pakhomova et al., 2007; Severmann et al., 2010). Assuming that the bottom water oxygen level remains favorable for the transfer of ferrous Fe across the benthic boundary for a prolonged period of time, the reactive Fe pool will become progressively depleted, unless it is replenished through detrital input. Such a scenario of reactive Fe depletion in sediments underlying a permanently anoxic but non-sulﬁdic water column is in agreement with Fe/ Al ratios signiﬁcantly below the detrital background in zones II and III (Fig. 5) and low concentrations of reactive Fe minerals in the central part of the OMZ reported by Suits and Arthur (2000). Apparently, detrital inputs from the continent are not suﬃcient to balance the reductive loss of Fe from sediments in this section of the Peruvian margin. Some of the released Fe seems to be laterally transported in the water column and re-oxidized and deposited at the oxycline in zone IV (~900-1100 m) where Fe/Al ratios increase above the detrital background (Fig. 5). Here, elevated bottom water oxygen levels (~<measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>, Table 2 and Fig. 2) prevent the Fe which is reduced in the sediments from being transported across the benthic boundary (Fig. 3). Therefore, most of the delivered excess Fe may be retained in the sediments. A similar export mechanism of reactive Fe has been reported for sediments of the Arabian and Mexican upwelling areas where sedimentary Fe/Al ratios are signiﬁcantly higher below than within the OMZ (Van der Weijden et al., 1999; Nameroﬀ et al., 2002). In analogy to Fe, increasing pore water Mn concentrations (Fig. 3) and diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes (Fig. 4) below zone III could imply a relative enrichment of Mn at the sediment surface in zone IV. However, because of its shallower reduction zone and sluggish oxidation kinetics compared to Fe, most of the Mn which is liberated at the sediment surface may diﬀuse back into the water column. As a consequence of this shallow recycling, any delivery of ‘excess’ Mn in zone IV is not recorded in the Mn/Al ratios (Fig. 5).</p>
    <p>The relatively high benthic Fe ﬂuxes observed at the shallowest station (BIGO-05) may partly be due to an increased supply of detrital (oxyhydr)oxides from the continent (Suits and Arthur, 2000). Another portion of the pore water Fe at the shelf stations, however, has likely been delivered from zones II and III through lateral transport of dissolved Fe in the water column and re-oxidation and deposition at the upper oxycline during periods of shelf oxygenation. Upon the recurrence of anoxic conditions (like those prevailing during our sampling campaign), this pool of excess Fe is reduced and partly recycled into the water column, thus leading to particularly high benthic ﬂuxes compared to stations in zones II and III. A similar alternation of particulate supply and reductive release may be anticipated for Mn which shows also higher pore water concentrations and diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes in zone I compared to zones II and III. As Mn/Al ratios in zone I are similarly low as in the other zones (Fig. 5), it is anticipated that accumulation of Mn during oxic periods and release during anoxic periods largely cancel out each other. In contrast, the Fe/Al ratios are equal to or slightly above the detrital background in zone I suggesting a more eﬃcient trapping of the reactive Fe which is delivered from land and the OMZ during periods of shelf oxygenation. This is in agreement with results from Suits and Arthur (2000) who reported the highest degrees of pyritization (DOPs) and the highest pyrite concentrations on the entire Peruvian margin for sediments on the shelf. The above discussion of Mn and Fe data reveals a complex interplay between reductive release, lateral transport, deposition and recycling across the margin. This framework of how redox gradients and oscillations aﬀect metal cycling in the Peruvian OMZ will be revisited and substantiated in the following discussion of U, V and Mo data.</p>
    <p>4.2. Controls on the benthic ﬂux of trace metals 4.2.1. Uranium Most sediment cores in zone II to zone IV show dissolved U concentrations decreasing downward from seawater-like values at the top to <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.0">1.0</num>-<num atMost="3.0">3.0</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num>-<num atMost="10">10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> below surface (Fig. 3). At greater sediment depth, U concentrations remain either constant or increase again in MUC15 and MUC53. In agreement with previous studies on anoxic marine sediments, the removal of U close to the sediment surface is attributed to reduction of U(VI) to U(IV) followed by precipitation of UO2 or other authigenic U phases (e.g. Barnes and Cochran, 1990, 1991; Klinkhammer and Palmer, 1991). The resulting downward diﬀusive U ﬂux increases between zone IV and zone II and reaches its highest value in MUC33 at <measure type="value"><num>376</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (Table 4, Fig. 4). Previous studies in a broad range of oxic and hypoxic marine settings revealed striking relationships between authigenic U accumulation and the organic carbon rain and degradation rates as well as the oxygen penetration depth (Zheng et al., 2002a; McManus et al., 2005; Morford et al., 2009a). All of these parameters dictate the extent of reducing conditions in the surface sediments and, therefore, the activity of Fe and sulfate reducing bacteria, both of which are capable of mediating U reduction (Lovley et al., 1991; Lovley and Phillips, 1992; Zheng et al., 2002a). During our sampling campaign, the Peru margin was characterized by a continuous landward decrease in bottom water oxygen concentration (Table 1, Fig. 2) and increasing carbon rain and degradation rates as well as Fe and sulfate reduction rates towards the shore (Bohlen et al., 2011). Furthermore, U depletion occurred generally at or shortly below the depth of the highest Fe concentrations (Fig. 3). These observations support the general conception that authigenic U accumulation is controlled by the combined rates of Fe and sulfate reduction close to the sediment/bottom water interface (Zheng et al., 2002a; McManus et al., 2005). At depths shallower than MUC33, surface sediments are still favorable for U reduction, which is demonstrated by maxima in dissolved Fe at <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> and bottom water oxygen concentrations close to zero. However, dissolved U concentrations above bottom water values at the sediment surface of MUC19 and particularly BIGO-T (Fig. 3) indicate a considerable diﬀusive U ﬂux out of the sediments (Table 4, Fig. 4). Furthermore, pore water U proﬁles in zone I do not show any regular U depletion but scatter around bottom water values. Similar U proﬁles have been observed in bioturbated and/or bioirrigated sediments underlying oxic bottom water (Zheng et al., 2002a; Morford et al., 2009a,b) or in estuaries with seasonal oxygen ﬂuctuations in the water column (Shaw et al., 1994). In such settings, authigenic U which had precipitated during more reducing periods undergoes transient re-oxidation and recycling through diﬀusion across the benthic boundary. Pore water U in zone I follows a highly transient zig-zag-pattern which may be ascribed to ENSO-related high amplitude changes between oxic and anoxic conditions. In contrast to that, the dissolved U distribution in MUC19 is much closer to steady state with respect to the present bottom water oxygen level (cf. MUC33). Accordingly, the continuous growth of the surﬁcial U peak between &gt;<measure type="value"><num atMost="320">320</num> and ~<num atLeast="250">250</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (MUC19, BIGO-T) and the absence of any pore water U depletion in zone I are attributed to the enhanced intensity, frequency and duration of oxygenation episodes with decreasing water depth (Gutiérrez et al., 2008).</p>
    <p>Zheng et al. (2002a) reported a threshold oxygen level of <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> above which U remobilization may occur. However, Levin et al. (2002) pointed out that even during the intense El Niño event of 1997/1998 the bottom water oxygen concentration at the deepest station where U remobilization is observed (MUC19) did not rise above ~<measure type="value"><num>2.2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>. Although the Peruvian margin experienced several positive ENSO periods in the years prior to our sampling campaign, there was no major El Niño event comparable to those of 1982/1983 and 1997/1998 (see Fig. A1 Appendix A for a time series of the Oceanic Niño Index, ONI). We therefore assume that even a minute increase in bottom water oxygen concentration (i.e. <measure type="value"><num>62</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>), shifting the U(VI)/U(IV) boundary by a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>, may be suﬃcient to cause shallow remobilization of authigenic U. The shift of the redox boundary is likely supported by reduced ﬂuxes of particulate organic carbon from the overlying water column during positive ENSO periods (Gutiérrez et al., 2000). Another factor that potentially enhances U remobilization is the activity of bioturbating organisms. Levin et al. (2002) and Gutiérrez et al. (2008) demonstrated that bioturbating fauna rapidly inhabits the Peruvian shelf and upper slope sediments during oxygenation episodes and even persists for several months after anoxic conditions have reestablished.</p>
    <p>4.2.2. Vanadium and molybdenum It has been argued in previous studies that downward diﬀusion of V and Mo across the sediment/bottom water interface due to authigenic removal is the primary mechanism of V and Mo accumulation in sediments on the Peruvian margin and other upwelling areas (Zheng et al., 2000; Böning et al., 2004, 2009). A downward directed concentration gradient across the sediment surface requires a shallow authigenic V and Mo sink. This sink must be highly eﬀective to prevent any excess V and Mo that is released from Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides from accumulating in pore water. Otherwise a shallow peak will establish promoting both an upward directed diﬀusive ﬂux across the benthic boundary and a downward ﬂux towards the authigenic sink. Most sediment cores in zones I to IV display dissolved V and Mo concentrations above local bottom water values in the uppermost section of the sediment column (~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>-<num atMost="10">10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>; Fig. 3). Some of these shallow peaks coincide with maxima in dissolved Mn and Fe suggesting a common supply or cycling of V and Mo with Mn and/or Fe. This is particularly the case in zone IV where both V and Mo display pronounced peaks in the Mn reduction zone (up to <measure type="value"><num>248</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> of V and <measure type="value"><num>179</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> of Mo). However, dissolution of Mn (oxyhydr)oxides alone is unlikely to account for the shallow V and Mo enrichment in pore water since diﬀusive benthic Mn ﬂuxes range in the same order of magnitude as the diffusive V and Mo ﬂuxes (Table 4, Fig. 4). For comparison, in other settings where release of V and Mo from Mn (oxyhydr)oxides has been postulated, dissolved Mn concentrations in pore water (and by inference the diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes) exceed those of V and Mo by several orders of magnitudes (Shaw et al., 1990; Morford et al., 2005).</p>
    <p>Surface sediments in zone IV receive high loads of reactive Fe that has been supplied from zones II and III through lateral transport within the anoxic water column and re-precipitation at the lower boundary of the OMZ (cf. Section 4.1). However, since the regeneration of V and Mo occurs at shallower sediment depth than Fe reduction, release during quantitative dissolution of Fe (oxyhydr)oxides cannot account for the surﬁcial V and Mo peaks either. In fact, the coinciding zones of V, Mo and Fe removal at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num>-<num atMost="3">3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> do rather suggest that most of the V and some of the Mo released at the sediment surface is re-adsorbed to Fe (oxyhydr)oxides shortly below. Another possible explanation for the shallow V and Mo accumulation in pore waters of zone IV is release form fragile organic substances in the thin oxic surface layer (Brumsack and Gieskes, 1983; Audry et al., 2006). Neither of the above explanations can be veriﬁed based on our data. However, since both V and Mo are attracted by metallic surfaces under oxic conditions (e.g. Chan and Riley, 1966a,b; Barling and Anbar, 2004; Goldberg et al., 2009) and since they are both liberated concomitantly with Mn we anticipate that some kind of particulate shuttle is involved. Below the shallow peaks, the presence of dissolved Fe and seawater-like V and Mo concentrations indicate that H2S concentrations in pore waters of zone IV are too low as to drive signiﬁcant V reduction or Mo sulﬁdation. As a consequence, most of the liberated V and Mo is lost through diffusion across the benthic boundary (see negative benthic ﬂuxes in Table 4 and Fig. 4). Again increasing concentrations below <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> indicate ongoing mobilization of V and Mo (and also U) below the depth of Mn and Fe recycling. This could be related to deep-reaching bioturbation and/or bioirrigation causing re-oxidation of authigenic metal phases that were precipitated during more reducing periods or at greater sediment depth (Morford et al., 2009b). This explanation is supported by ﬁndings of Levin et al. (2002) who reported a comparably high abundance of burrowing fauna below the permanent OMZ. Pore water proﬁles in zone I and the shallowest core in zone II (BIGO-T) display somewhat erratic V and Mo peaks both within and below the Mn and Fe reduction zones. Release from either Mn or Fe (oxyhydr)oxides cannot be distinguished at the given sampling resolution. However, the coincident Mn, Fe and Mo increase in the uppermost cm (Fig. 3) and the high upward diﬀusive Mn, Fe and Mo ﬂuxes (Table 4, Fig. 4) in zone I suggest some Mo release from dissolving (oxyhydr)oxides. The lack of a signiﬁcant benthic V ﬂux might be related to shallow re-adsorption of V(IV) species that are known to form in manganous or ferruginous pore waters (e.g. Calvert and Pedersen, 1993). Below the Mn and Fe reduction zone and up to a depth of ~<measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>, pore water proﬁles of V and Mo display a similar zig-zag-pattern as the U proﬁles. These transient irregularities indicate that V and Mo are also aﬀected by remobilization during periods of shelf oxygenation. The pore water Mo proﬁle of MUC29 in zone I shows a steep decrease below <measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> which is coincident with the accumulation of H2S (Fig. 3). This is in excellent agreement with the general conception of Mo being scavenged from pore water at a critical threshold concentration of H2S (Helz et al., 1996; Erickson and Helz, 2000; Zheng et al., 2000). Intense Mo authigenesis close to the sediment surface would theoretically support a downward diﬀusive Mo ﬂux across the benthic boundary. However, because of the shallow accumulation of dissolved Mo from metal (oxyhydr)oxides and re-dissolved authigenic phases, the actual benthic ﬂux in MUC29 is directed out of the sediment (Table 4 and Fig. 4). At greater depth than BIGO-T, re-oxidation occurs less frequently, which should favor shallow Mo authigenesis and diﬀusive resupply from the bottom water. Both MUC19 and MUC33 in zone II display sharp concentration gradients at or shortly below the sediment surface and a Mo minimum at shallow depth (&lt;<measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> at 3-5 cm; Fig. 3). We did not detect any shallow H2S in MUC19 and MUC33. However, the threshold level for sulﬁdation of molybdate and Mo-Fe-S co-precipitation reported by Zheng et al. (2000) is clearly below the detection limit of our H2S method (~<measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>). Therefore, active Mo authigenesis might have occurred at the time of sampling. Both MUC19 and MUC33 display TOC maxima at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num> to <num atMost="7">7</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> depth (see Supplementary EA-Table 2 in the Electronic Annex) suggesting that hot spots of H2S production are associated with organic-rich micro niches. MUC33 is the only core where a signiﬁcant downward benthic Mo ﬂux was observed in this study (Table 4). In this permanently anoxic area of the Peruvian margin, the development of a downward decreasing Mo gradient across the benthic boundary is likely favored by the continuous stripping of Mn and Fe in the water column and the surface sediments, respectively (see Section 4.1). Because of the strong Mn and Fe depletion arising from that (Fig. 5), sediment particles provide little adsorption sites for Mo which would then impede the downward benthic ﬂux upon its release during early sediment diagenesis. Pore water proﬁles of V and Mo in zone III are more heterogeneous and generally somewhat scattered. This is commonly observed in continental margin sediments (e.g. Shaw et al., 1990; Morford et al., 2005) and has been assigned to H2S production in microenvironments (Zheng et al., 2000) and the contrasting solubility of V and Mo species in manganous or ferruginous versus sulﬁdic pore waters (Calvert and Pedersen, 1993; Algeo and Maynard, 2004). Furthermore, zone III is located at the transition between the permanently anoxic and the hypoxic section of the Peruvian margin (Table 1, Fig. 2). Although ﬂuctuations in bottom water oxygenation are less frequent and vigorous here compared to zone I, non-steady state diagenesis might have contributed to the irregular shape of the pore water proﬁles. The negative excursions in the Mo proﬁles of zone III may indicate some Mo authigenesis in distinct depth intervals. However, Mo concentrations are always Pbottom water values suggesting that pore waters are generally not sulﬁdic enough as to support an appreciable downward benthic Mo ﬂux. Authigenic removal of V(IV) may also take place under non-sulﬁdic conditions (e.g. Calvert and Pedersen, 1993), which could explain the downward benthic V ﬂux in MUC21 and MUC39 (Table 4). In summary, the pore water V and Mo data suggest that direct diﬀusive supply of V and particularly Mo is limited to sediments in a narrow depth range underlying the most persistent and pronounced OMZ (~ &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="320">320</num> to <num atMost="400">400</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>). In the other areas, V and Mo are rather delivered with solid carriers such as detrital particles whose surfaces are coated with metallic (oxyhydr)oxides. Strictly speaking, this interpretation is only valid for the exact time of our sampling campaign. However, the sampling was conducted following a 1-year-lasting negative ENSO period (see Fig. A1 Appendix A) and during the season of most intense upwelling (e.g. Scheidegger and Krissek, 1983). It is unlikely, that conditions are much more favorable for diffusive V and Mo supply during other, presumably more oxic periods.</p>
    <p>4.3. Long-term accumulation of trace metals All of the three trace elements investigated show highest Al-normalized concentrations in zone II, coincident with the TOC maximum (Fig. 5). At greater water depth, V and Mo concentrations drop rapidly to the detrital background whereas U concentrations remain elevated on the entire continental margin. The opposite is observed on the shelf, where U and V concentrations drop abruptly at depth 6 BIGO-T whereas Mo concentrations decrease more gradually. These patterns are generally in good agreement with previously published data for the Peruvian upwelling area (Böning et al., 2004). Table 5 shows a compilation SRs, MARs and authigenic metal MARs for selected cores (see Supplementary EAFig. 1 in the Electronic Annex for proﬁles of excess 210Pb and model ﬁts). Dividing the SRs by the length of the respective cores reveals that the study intervals cover a time span of approximately <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="300">300</num> (MUC29) to <num atMost="1000">1000</num> (MUC19) <measure type="LENGTH" unit="yr">yr</measure></measure>. A comparison of diﬀusive benthic U, V and Mo ﬂuxes with authigenic MARs is provided in Fig. 4. The above deﬁned depth range, encompassing the most persistent and pronounced OMZ (~ &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="320">320</num> to <num atMost="400">400</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> or 78.15-78.25°W), is the only area where the diﬀusive supply of all trace metals investigated is broadly in agreement with their total authigenic MARs (extrapolating the authigenic MAR of MUC19 to the neighboring core MUC33). In the remaining areas, the lack of agreement between these two calculated parameters could reﬂect temporal variability in pore water chemistry. However, as ENSO conditions were negative during the <measure type="value"><num>12</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="months">months</measure></measure> preceding our sampling campaign, it may be anticipated that redox conditions on the Peruvian margin were rather favorable for diﬀusive V and Mo supply (see Fig. A1 Appendix A and previous section). This, along with the striking mismatch between the highest U MARs (zone IV) and the location of the permanent OMZ, suggests that mechanisms other than diﬀusion across the benthic boundary should be considered for trace metal supply and/or accumulation in the remaining areas.</p>
    <p>Compilation of sedimentation rates (SR) <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr-1">cm kyr-1</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>26</num><measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr-1">cm kyr-1</measure></measure> See Supplementary EA-Fig. 1 in the Electronic Annex for proﬁles of
excess 210Pb and model ﬁts. Approximate SR and MAR derived from Reimers and Suess (1983). <measure type="value"><num>81</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr-1">cm kyr-1</measure></measure> Dry bulk density was estimated from TOC using an empirical relationship that is based on data for Peru upwelling sediments from Böning et al. <measure type="value"><num>58</num> <measure type="SEDIMENTATION_RATE" unit="cm kyr-1">cm kyr-1</measure></measure></p>
    <p>Mass accumulation rates (MARs) and authigenic metal MARs for selected cores: a) <measure type="value"><num>8</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g cm-2 kyr-1">g cm-2 kyr-1</measure></measure>.</p>
    <p>Approximate SR and MAR <measure type="value"><num>18</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g cm-2 kyr-1">g cm-2 kyr-1</measure></measure> and b) <measure type="value"><num>53</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g cm-2 kyr-1">g cm-2 kyr-1</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>51</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="g cm-2 kyr-1">g cm-2 kyr-1</measure></measure></p>
    <p>4.3.1. Solid phase speciation of uranium Authigenic U MARs in zone IV exceed the corresponding benthic ﬂuxes by a factor of up to <measure type="value"><num>20</num></measure> and are higher than any of the benthic ﬂuxes hitherto reported for anoxic marine sediments (up to <measure type="value"><num>1.52</num> <measure type="MASS_ACCUMULATION_RATE" unit="nmol cm-2 yr-1">nmol cm-2 yr-1</measure></measure> in the California Borderland Basins; Zheng et al., 2002a). The only known additional source of authigenic U to marine sediments is particulate non-lithogenic U (PNU) in sinking organic matter (Anderson et al., 1989a; Zheng et al., 2002a,b). Preservation of PNU is favored by the persistent anoxia in the Peruvian OMZ (Zheng et al., 2002b). Moreover, the distribution of U/Al ratios and TOC concentrations across the margin is highly correlated (Fig. 5, R2 = <measure type="value"><num>0.79</num></measure>, n = <measure type="value"><num>148</num></measure>) suggesting that organic matter plays more than an indirect role for the authigenic accumulation of U. The plausibility of PNU as an important U source to the sediment may be evaluated by comparing the U/TOC ratios of water column particulate matter and surface sediments. Unfortunately, we do not dispose of U/TOC ratios for particulate matter oﬀ Peru. Zheng et al. (2002) reported U/TOC ratios of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.33 × 10-4">0.33</num>-<num atMost="0.45 × 10-4">0.45 × 10-4</num></measure> for water column particulate matter in the NE Paciﬁc, oﬀshore California. The U/TOC ratios of surface sediments in zone I (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.64 × 10-4">0.64</num>-<num atMost="0.94 × 10-4">0.94</num></measure>) are broadly in agreement with this range. Moreover, Hirose and Sugimura (1991) pointed out, that U/TOC ratios in sinking organic matter increase exponentially over more than one order of magnitude with increasing primary productivity. Considering the particularly high primary productivity in Peru coastal waters (Pennington et al., 2006), most of the U/TOC ratios in surface sediments (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.64 × 10-4">0.64</num>-<num atMost="2.1 × 10-4">2.1 × 10-4</num></measure>) are in agreement with a high contribution of PNU to the overall U supply. However PNU is unlikely the burial phase causing the diﬀerence between diﬀusive and total U accumulation in zones III and IV (Fig. 4). This is illustrated in Fig. 6, a plot of U/TOC ratios against sediment depth. The U/TOC ratios in zones I and II are either constant or increase in the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> to values of ~<measure type="value"><num>2.5</num></measure>. This is in agreement with organic matter degradation as well as U reduction and precipitation from pore water. In contrast to that, U/TOC ratios in zone III are more heterogeneous with maximum values as high as <measure type="value"><num>12 × 10-4</num></measure> shortly below the sediment surface. These values are far too high as to be explained with PNU as the primary host phase. Consequently, some mechanism of diagenetic redistribution has to be considered. Because of strong bottom currents and the associated eﬀects of reworking and winnowing, zone III reveals low net sedimentation rates (Table 5), which favors the formation and accumulation of phosphorite crusts and nodules (Reimers and Suess, 1983; Glenn and Arthur, 1988). In agreement with this general observation, numerous macroscopic phosphorite concretions were recovered from the MUCs in zone III and previous studies revealed increasing P concentrations and P/C ratios across the Peruvian margin (Böning et al., 2004). Phosphorites are known to be enriched in U with respect to both the detrital background and the surrounding sediment matrix (Veeh et al., 1974; Jarvis et al., 1994) and Böning et al. (2004) reported a good correlation between U and P for a sediment core from the Peruvian slope (<measure type="value"><num>598</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth). Combining the average inorganic P concentration (i.e. corrected for the organic P content) of <measure type="value"><num>1.9</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="wt.%">wt.%</measure></measure> reported for this core by Böning et al. (2004) with the range of U concentrations published by Arning et al. (2009) for phosphorite crusts from the Peruvian margin (~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="150">150</num>-<num atMost="280">280</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µg g-1">µg g-1</measure></measure> or U/P ratio of ~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.9 × 10-4">0.9</num>-<num atMost="1.7 × 10-4">1.7 × 10-4</num></measure>) yields phosphorite-bound U concentrations of ~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="17">17</num>-<num atMost="32">32</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µg g-1">µg U g-1</measure></measure> bulk sediment. This calculation further substantiates the assumption of Böning et al. (2004) that authigenic phosphorite is most likely an important host for U in Peru slope sediments (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="80">80</num>-<num atMost="250">250</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the U MAR in zone III). Glenn and Arthur (1988) emphasized the role of lateral sediment transport and reorganization for the enrichment of phosphorites on the Peruvian slope. Sediment MARs increase below zone II (Table 5) leading to increasing authigenic U MARs (Fig. 4), despite a general decrease in U/Al (Fig. 5). It is therefore anticipated that much of the U buried in zones III and IV is of allochthonous origin, i.e. has originally accumulated further upslope. The ultimate origin of the phosphorite-bound U (dissolved U in pore water versus PNU) and the mode of incorporation (inorganic versus microbial mechanism) cannot be resolved based on our data. However, in consideration of the apparent imbalance between diﬀusive and total U supply in most areas on the Peruvian margin, at least some of the U buried is likely delivered as PNU or another, yet unidentiﬁed U phase.</p>
    <p>4.3.2. V-Mo-U covariation in Peru upwelling sediments The lowest authigenic MARs of V and Mo as well as the lowest V/Al and Mo/Al ratios are observed in zone IV and the deepest core in zone III (Figs. 4 and 5). This in agreement with the pore water data suggesting that redox conditions below the permanent OMZ are not reducing enough as to enable a downward benthic ﬂux or an eﬃcient authigenic removal of the V and Mo that is released from solid carriers. Lateral input of phosphorite-rich sediments from further upslope cannot compensate for that, since authigenic phosphorites do not sequester V or Mo to a signiﬁcant extent (Jarvis et al., 1994). The small but still signiﬁcant V MAR observed in zone IV might be related to lateral supply of some other authigenic V phase from further upslope or to re-adsorption of V(IV) to refractory Fe (oxyhydr)oxides. In sharp contrast to U, authigenic MARs of V and Mo are most pronounced in MUC29 in zone I where they exceed all of the benthic ﬂuxes observed in this study. A similar mismatch between diﬀusive and total authigenic Mo supply has been postulated (though not proven based on pore water data) for weakly restricted basins with redox variations at short time scales (e.g. Saanich Inlet and Cariaco Basin) (Algeo and Lyons, 2006; Algeo and Tribovillard, 2009). In such settings, vertical ﬂuctuations of the chemocline alternately promote (i) Mo scavenging by Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides that precipitate in the water column during oxic periods and (ii) reductive recycling of the Mn and Fe at the sediment surface as well as sulﬁdation and ﬁxation of the released Mo during anoxic periods (Berrang and Grill, 1974; Adelson et al., 2001; Algeo and Lyons, 2006). This particulate shuttle leads to an enhanced supply of particle-reactive elements as compared to those that are chieﬂy delivered by molecular diﬀusion (e.g. U) (Algeo and Tribovillard, 2009). On the Peruvian shelf, the continuous displacement of the upper boundary of the OMZ likely exerts a similar eﬀect on Mo cycling. During periods of shelf oxygenation, surface sediments receive particulate Mo associated with terrigenous Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides. This terrigenous supply is particularly pronounced during El Niño events, when otherwise arid coastal Peru receives heavy rainfall resulting in enhanced continental erosion and runoﬀ (Wells, 1990). Moreover, additional (oxyhydr)oxides are likely supplied through reoxidation and precipitation of dissolved Mn and Fe at the retreating upper oxycline of the OMZ. After the recurrence of anoxic conditions, the (oxyhydr)oxides are reductively dissolved and recycled whereas the hereby liberated Mo is removed into authigenic phases. This scenario is in excellent agreement with the pore water Mo proﬁle of MUC29, indicating both Mo release and authigenic removal, as well as the relatively high upward directed benthic ﬂuxes of Mn and Fe in zone I compared to zones II and III. Moreover, a particulate shuttle, driven by ENSO-related ﬂuctuations in bottom water oxygenation, is a viable explanation for the decoupling of U and Mo accumulation on the Peruvian shelf. However, the pore water proﬁles in zone I do not only indicate Mo release from metal (oxyhydr)oxides but also Mo, V and U remobilization. Consequently, not only preferential supply but also preferential loss of speciﬁc elements has to be considered in this discussion. Further insights into the diﬀerent modes of trace metal supply versus remobilization may be obtained from cross plots of authigenic Mo versus authigenic V und U concentrations (Fig. 7). Concomitantly increasing authigenic V and Mo concentrations in zones IV and III (Fig. 7a) reﬂect the decreasing sediment redox potential determined by decreasing bottom water oxygen concentrations towards the core of the OMZ. MUC33 and MUC19 in zone II display a separate trend implying a relative increase in the eﬃciency of V accumulation. This is likely related to the abrupt TOC increase from ~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num> to &gt;<num atMost="10">10</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="wt.%">wt.%</measure></measure> at the transition between zones III and II (Fig. 5). Refractory organic matter is an important host phase for reduced V species (Breit and Wanty, 1991) and Algeo and Maynard (2004) reported a TOC threshold of ~<measure type="value"><num>7</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="wt.%">wt.%</measure></measure> beyond which they detected a signiﬁcant increase in V accumulation in Pennsylvanian black shales. The V accumulation in zone II is likely favored by the ubiquity of refractory organic compounds providing binding sites for the reduced V in pore water. In contrast, Mo resides primarily in sulﬁdic phases in anoxic sediments (Huerta-Diaz and Morse, 1992; Algeo and Maynard, 2004; Tribovillard et al., 2004) and any inﬂuence of the TOC content would be rather indirect, i.e. by determining the intensity of sulfate reduction (McManus et al., 2006). The highest authigenic V and Mo concentrations are observed in BIGO-T, the shallowest core in zone II. Pore water proﬁles of this core indicate redox oscillations in the water column (Fig. 3) suggesting that a signiﬁcant portion of the V and Mo has been shuttled by metal (oxyhydr)oxides. At the transition to zone I, however, authigenic V concentrations decrease abruptly whereas Mo concentrations in MUC29 are still higher than in most samples of zones II and III. This is unlikely due to preferential Mo supply with particulate matter, since V has a higher aﬃnity to Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides than Mo (Takematsu et al., 1985). Alternatively, reduced retention of authigenic V during oxygenation periods might be the reason for the decoupling. The major diagenetic sink of Mo is Fe sulﬁdes (pyrite and structurally similar Mo-Fe-S phases) (Bostick et al., 2003; Vorlicek et al., 2004) whereas V does not enter sulﬁde minerals to a signiﬁcant extent (Huerta- Diaz and Morse, 1992; Scholz and Neumann, 2007). Con- centrations of TS in MUC29 are among the highest observed throughout this study. Moreover, TS is decoupled from TOC in zone I (Fig. 5), which clearly indicates enhanced preservation of sulfur with respect to organic carbon. As mentioned in Section 4.1, Suits and Arthur (2000) reported the highest pyrite concentrations and DOP values throughout the Peruvian margin (12.0-13.5°S) for sediments on the shelf. The high pyrite concentrations have been assigned to the enhanced availability of reactive Fe compounds. Furthermore, Suits and Arthur (2000) hypothesized that pyrite formation on the Peruvian shelf is particularly favored by ENSO-related redox oscillations. This is related to the enhanced formation of sulfur intermediates (S0 , S2O32-, Sn2- ) from H2S under slightly oxidizing conditions, which in turn stimulates the conversion of Fe monosulﬁdes (FeS) to pyrite via the polysulﬁde pathway (Schoonen and Barnes, 1991; Schoonen, 2004; Rickard and Morse, 2005). In addition, experimental work by Vorlicek et al. (2004) has revealed that polysulﬁdes (Sn20) do also promote the conversion of MoOS 3 to MoS 4, which is the ultimate step for the long-term ﬁxation of Mo onto authigenic pyrite. As a consequence, Mo accumulation and burial is rather favored than perturbed by transient oxygenation on the Peruvian shelf. In contrast to that, V(III) is readily oxidized to V(V) under oxic conditions leading to a destabilization of authigenic V oxides and hydroxides (Wehrli and Stumm, 1989). Another factor that potentially limits the accumulation of authigenic V on the shelf is the enhanced carbon turnover and reduced preservation of refractory organic compounds under increasingly oxic conditions (Sun et al., 1993, 2002). This assumption is corroborated by the combined observations of decreasing TOC concentrations (Fig. 5) but increasing organic matter degradation rates in the landward direction across the Peruvian shelf (Bohlen et al., in press). The discrimating eﬀect of redox oscillations on the longterm accumulation of diﬀerent trace metals is most evident in Fig. 7b, a cross plot of authigenic Mo versus authigenic U concentrations. Concomitantly increasing authigenic Mo and U concentrations between zone IV and MUC19 in zone II (Fig. 7b) are in agreement with the increasing diﬀusive benthic ﬂuxes and reﬂect the decreasing benthic redox potential towards the central OMZ. At shallower depth, however, authigenic U concentrations decrease dramatically while Mo concentrations continue to increase. One reason for this decoupling is that U does not adsorb to (oxyhydr)oxides in the water column and therefore does not participate in the particulate shuttle (cp. Algeo and Tribovillard, 2009). Another reason, however, is most likely related to the strong susceptibility to re-oxidation of authigenic U. It was argued in Section 4.2.1 that pore water U proﬁles on the Peruvian shelf are strongly aﬀected by remobilization. The re-oxidized and dissolved authigenic U in pore water induces an upward concentration gradient and thus impedes any additional U accumulation. Thus, the combined evidence of our pore water and sediment data strongly suggest that reduced uptake and preferential loss of U during oxygenation periods is of equal importance for the decoupling of U and Mo accumulation on the Peruvian shelf.</p>
    <p>4.4. Implication for the use of U-Mo systematics as paleoredox proxy A number of studies have proposed to use Mo and U systematics to gain information about paleo-redox conditions (Algeo and Lyons, 2006; McManus et al., 2006; Algeo and Tribovillard, 2009). This approach is of great relevance for upwelling areas or other oxygen-deﬁcient settings where recent studies have attempted to reconstruct past OMZ extension and/or ENSO variability (e.g. Nameroﬀ et al., 2004; Gutiérrez et al., 2009; Dı́az-Ochoa et al., 2011). McManus et al. (2006) derived an empirical relationship between sedimentary U/Mo ratios and oxygen concentrations in bottom water. Disregarding MUC27 at <measure type="value"><num>2025</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> water depth, U/Mo ratios decrease upslope across the Peruvian margin (Fig. 8) and broadly retrace the bottom water oxygen concentration at the time of sampling (Table 1). However, the corresponding correlation trend is quite diﬀerent from the one presented by McManus et al. (2006) (Fig. 9a) suggesting that any relationship to bottom water oxygen is of rather regional relevance. Major deviations from the trend by McManus et al. (2006) are observed in zone I where ﬂuctuations in bottom water oxygenation enhance Mo accumulation (through particulate supply) and diminish U accumulation (through remobilization) thus pushing the U/Mo ratios to lower values. By contrast, comparably high U/Mo ratios in zones III and IV are attributed to the relative enrichment of U over Mo in authigenic phosphorites which are particularly abundant on the Peruvian slope. McManus et al. (2006) suggested that their empirical relationship is in fact due to increasing sulfate reduction rates and thus an increased availability of dissolved H2S in pore water with decreasing oxygen concentrations in bottom water. This assumption is in agreement with our ﬁndings on U and Mo diagenesis in Peru upwelling sediments and further corroborated by the exponential relationship observed between U/Mo ratios and sediment TS (including MUC27, Fig. 9b). The non-linearity of this relationship is not surprising, given that U reduction is mediated by both Fe- and sulfate-reducing bacteria whereas authigenic Mo ﬁxation requires the presence of H2S. In light of these ﬁndings, U/Mo ratios in sediments or sedimentary rocks might be used to constrain whether shallow pore waters were ferruginous or (at least temporarily) sulﬁdic at the time of deposition. This could be also a promising approach to trace the past location of the lower boundary of the Peruvian OMZ where U/Mo ratios rapidly drop at the transition from zone IV to III (Fig. 8). However, as for the relationship between U/Mo and bottom water oxygen, variable processes of sediment redistribution on the slope may complicate the interpretation of paleo-records. It is important to note that the use of U/Mo ratios obscures the decoupling of U with respect to Mo on the Peruvian shelf (Figs. 8 and 9), although this holds great potential for the reconstruction of past oxygen ﬂuctuations in bottom water. Algeo and Tribovillard (2009) presented sedimentary U and Mo concentrations in cross plots of enrichment factors in order to illustrate multiple controls on U-Mo covariation in oxygen-deﬁcient marine systems. They identiﬁed distinct arrays (dashed lines in Fig. 10) indicating (i) concomitantly increasing U and Mo accumulation with decreasing benthic redox potential in open-ocean upwelling areas and (ii) preferential accumulation of Mo over U in weakly restricted basins with a particulate shuttle in the water column. These U-Mo covariation patterns were then used to reconstruct depositional conditions in paleo-marine systems. Plotting our Mo and U data from the Peruvian margin in a cross plot of enrichment factors yields additional information on how bottom water oxygen ﬂuctuations in open-ocean settings may aﬀect U-Mo systematics. The trend line of shelf cores in Fig. 7b (curved arrow) appears as a straight line in Fig. 10 (linear regression through samples of zone I and BIGO-T). This line is almost identical to the trend of weakly restricted basins with a particulate shuttle in the water column of Algeo and Tribovillard (2009). We have identiﬁed a similar mechanism on the Peruvian margin. However, in contrast to restricted basins, where the chemocline ﬂuctuates up and down, the OMZ boundaries move rather laterally across a ﬂat shelf leading to a transition between areas where mostly oxic and others where mostly anoxic conditions in bottom water prevail. Although enhanced Mo supply with coated particulates is an important aspect of this environment, preferential loss of U during oxic periods is almost certainly of equal importance for the characteristic U-Mo pattern observed. Keeping that in mind, cross plots of Mo versus U like those in Figs. 7b and 10 could be of great use for the reconstruction of past OMZ variability and redox oscillations in ancient open-ocean environments in general.</p>
    <p>5. SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS We have investigated the spatial and temporal variability of trace metal diagenesis (U, V and Mo) across the Peru upwelling area. Our ﬁndings are summarized in a conceptual model consisting of two end member situations that  A: Within the permanent OMZ, U, V and Mo diﬀuse across the sediment/bottom water interface and precipitate in the zones of Fe and sulfate reduction. Since Mn reduction is largely completed in the water column, sediments receive little Mn-bound, particulate V and Mo. This favors the establishment of a downward directed benthic V and Mo ﬂux. Because of the permanently anoxic but non-sulﬁdic conditions in the bottom water, surface sediments within the OMZ are subject to a continuous diﬀusive loss of Fe. Some of the dissolved Mn and Fe in the water column are re-precipitated at the oxyclines and deposited at the lower and upper boundary of the OMZ. B: Sediments below the OMZ receive particulate V and Mo with metal (oxyhydr)oxides that have precipitated at the lower oxycline. This particulate V and Mo is released into the pore water upon Mn and Fe reduction. Since pore waters below the OMZ are generally not suﬃciently sulﬁdic for an eﬃcient authigenic removal, most of the liberated V and Mo is lost through upward diﬀusion across the benthic boundary. Intense U accumulation below the OMZ is attributed to both in situ reduction of U in the Fe reduction zone and lateral input of U-rich phosphorites from further upslope. The long term accumulation of V, Mo and U below the OMZ is diminished by the activity of bioturbating and bioirrigating organisms. C: Sediments on the Peruvian shelf are strongly aﬀected by ENSO-related oxygen ﬂuctuations in bottom water. During positive ENSO periods, when bottom waters on the shelf are oxic, terrigenous Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides as well as metal (oxyhydr)oxides that have precipitated at the retreating oxycline shuttle V and Mo to the sediment surface. After the recurrence of anoxic conditions, the Mn and Fe (oxyhydr)oxides are reductively recycled thus leading to high benthic Mn and Fe ﬂuxes as compared to the permanent OMZ. Upon dissolution of the particulate carriers, the adsorbed V and Mo are released into the pore water and authigenically removed in the sulfate reduction zone. This alternation between supply of particle-reactive trace metals during oxic periods and authigenic ﬁxation during anoxic periods leads to a preferential accumulation of V and Mo over U on the Peruvian shelf. The decoupling between V, Mo and U accumulation is further accentuated by the varying susceptibility to re-oxidation of the diﬀerent authigenic metal phases. While authigenic V and U are readily re-oxidized and recycled during oxygenation periods, Mo accumulation with authigenic pyrite is favored by the occasional occurrence of slightly oxidizing conditions. ENSO-related redox ﬂuctuations in bottom water are likely to aﬀect metal cycling along the entire SE Paciﬁc ocean margin and similar phenomena might have occurred in ancient oceans through earth history. This study reveals that relative enrichments and/or depletions of redox-sensitive trace metals (most notably Mo and U) are sensitive to short-term ﬂuctuations in bottom water oxygenation. The next step will be to apply this concept downcore in order to reconstruct past OMZ extension and variability as well as to identify large-scale redox ﬂuctuations in the geological record.</p>
    <p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS We are indebted to the IFM-GEOMAR technicians A. Bleyer, M. Dibbern, B. Domeyer, R. Ebbinghaus, A. Petersen and R. Surberg for their enthusiastic help and cooperation during the M77 cruises and the post-cruise work in Kiel. Furthermore, we would like to thank the oﬃcers and crew of RV Meteor for their commitment during the sampling campaign. Constructive and insightful comments from Thomas J. Algeo, Nicolas Tribovillard and one anonymous reviewer as well as from the associate editor, George R. Helz, are greatly appreciated. This work is a contribution of the Sonderforschungsbereich 754 “Climate-Biogeochemistry Interactions in the Tropical Ocean” (www.sfb754.de/en/) which is supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft.</p>
  </text>
</tei>
