<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2020-09-01T09:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
        <p>We have measured the temperature dependent resistivity of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="7">7</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> using a turnbuckle DAC (diamond anvil cell) and in magnetic field up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>. Unlike many other organic conductors, a <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistance was observed in the superconducting state even under high pressures. Superconductivity was observed over a range of P = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.18">4.18</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="6.03">6.03</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> and showed a peak T c of <measure type="value"><num>2.25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> at <measure type="value"><num>4.58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The temperature dependence of the upper critical magnetic field H c2 (T) was determined via resistivity at P = <measure type="value"><num>4.58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, for the intrachain (a), interchain (b), and interlayer (c *) configurations and the H c2 (T) displays positive curvature without saturation, which may be originated by a FFLO state, for magnetic field along a-axis and b-axis in T ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.5">0.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for P = <measure type="value"><num>4.48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. This feature is suppressed with increasing pressure and the orbital pair breaking mechanism becomes dominant. The values of the Ginzberg-Landau coherence length for <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> different axes obtained from this work shows that (TMTTF) PF 6 is an anisotropic threedimensional superconductor.</p>
        <p>The Bechgaard salt (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 (TMTSF = tetramethyltetraselenafulvalene) was the first organic superconductor discovered in <measure type="value"><num when="1980">1980</num></measure> with a superconducting temperature of T c = <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> (critical pressure, P c = <measure type="value"><num>1.2</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>). 1 Since this discovery, materials based on TMTSF and its derivatives, such as TMTTF (tetramethyltetrathiofulvalene), the so-called (TMTCF) 2 X (X = monovalent anion) series, have been investigated extensively to search for more superconductors. 2, 3,4,5 They have also attracted attention for <measure type="value"><num>many</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> due to their rich properties such as spin-Peierls (SP), charge-ordering, spin density wave (SDW) and possible unconventional superconductivity (SC) that appear by changing counter anion or applying external pressures. 6 Many compounds with TMTSF molecules exhibit a SC state at low pressures around <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> 6,7 whereas most compounds with TMTTF exhibit a SC transition at ultra-high pressures, for example P c = <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> in (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 . 8,9 Taking advantage of low pressure induced <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num></measure> and <measure type="value"><measure type="PRESSURE">ambient pressure</measure></measure> 11,12 superconductivity, the studies especially on the SC phase and its upper critical field have been done extensively with TMTSF salts, but not many with TMTTF salts.</p>
        <p>A generic phase diagram was obtained by studies of many different materials among the -TMTCF series at ambient and high pressure, combining the trends seen with chemical pressure and external pressure. 3,4,7 The (chemical) pressure that each material displays on the phase diagram shows degrees of <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-dimensionality caused by many factors such as size of anion, distance between molecule planes, distance between Selenium/Sulfur atoms and Coulomb repulsion between conducting electrons. However, for layered organic material like TMTCF salts, the a-axis direction is most compressive where TMTCF planes have weak van der Waals bonding due to overlapping π orbits and it is least compressive along the c-axis direction where the TMTCF molecule and anion have ion bonding even though the applied external pressure is highly hydrostatic. In the case of (TMTSF) PF 6 , it is compressed by <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="?" unit="%/kbar">%/kbar</measure></measure> along a-axis while the normal directions are an order of magnitude less compressive <measure type="value"><num>13</num></measure> when <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="kbar">kbar</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>0.3</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>) of hydrostatic pressure is applied. Therefore, even with the hydrostatic pressures, electronic structure changes anisotropically, the dimensionality of the system changes as well, and degrees of the change vary depending on the size of the anion and type of cation. It is an open question if we can treat chemical pressures and external pressures in exactly the same manner. So, by changing external physical pressure on different designer molecules to gather information, one hopes to achieve a universal understanding of quasi 1-dimensional organic conductors, (TMTCF) 2 X series which might also be relevant to other low dimensional system.</p>
        <p>Due to the technical difficulty of applying hydrostatic pressures to fragile organic compounds at low temperatures and magnetic fields to study the superconducting state, the anisotropy of the upper critical field (H c2 ) in TMTTF salts had not been determined prior to this work. In the present work, the anisotropy of H c2 in (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 was determined via resistivity at temperatures as low as T = <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> and in magnetic fields up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> which also complement previously reported work. 9,14</p>
        <p>Single crystals of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 were synthesised by the electrochemical method . The dimensions of the crystal selected for resistivity measurements was ∼<measure type="list"><num>150</num>×<num>30</num>×<num>20</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> 3 . The electric resistivity was measured by the standard <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure>-probe method with AC current (I = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>∼<num atMost="50">50</num> <measure type="ELECTRIC_CURRENT" unit="µA">µA</measure></measure>) parallel to a-axis (intra chain).</p>
        <p>This measurement was carried out in a He refrigerator with a <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> magnet. Pressure was generated by using a turnbuckle type diamond anvil cell (DAC). The diamond culets are <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> in diameter, which are separated by a gasket indented to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="65">65</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> that has a <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> hole as a sample chamber. Details of this pressure apparatus are discussed elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Graphite paint was used to make electrical contacts between the leads of pressed gold wires (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> in diameter) and the sample. The sample was placed inside a cavity with a liquid pressure medium, glycerin which was proven to transmit nearly hydrostatic pressure up to GPa 17 , in the gasket which is placed in between <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> diamonds. The pressure is calibrated at low temperatures by monitoring the shift in the fluorescence of a ruby chip located in the cavity near the sample at T = <measure type="value"><num>77</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. 18 The DAC used in this study tends to gain pressure as it is cooled down from room temperature to below liquid nitrogen temperature where the pressure stabilizes. During the measurements for H//b the probe had to be warmed up to above liquid nitrogen temperature a few times, with the result being different normal state resistive values. It is extremely difficult to calculate the absolute value of resistivity from transport measurements using a DAC on organic materials. This is due to the amount of conducting paint which is relatively large for the small sample and inaccurate determinations of the distance between contacts and the cross section area of the sample. Therefore we used the data from resistivity measurements of the same crystal using a Cubic Anvil Press for pressurization for normalizing our data at room temperature. 14 The magnetic field was applied along a, b and c * axis and the temperature dependence of the resistivity was measured over the pressure range of P = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.37">4.37</num> -<num atMost="5.64">5.64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> at low temperatures. The orientation of the sample was adjusted by changing the angles of the DAC with respect to the probe when mounting.</p>
        <p>In the generic P − T (pressure-temperature) phase diagram 3,4,19 , the ground state of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 becomes an AF/SDW from SP at around <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> then becomes a SC phase at around <measure type="value"><num>4</num>. <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, metallic behaviour is observed over the complete temperature range. The highest T c was observed near the pressure at which the SDW phase vanished. The SC phase in the vicinity of the SDW phase was observed at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.18">4.18</num> ≤ P ≤ <num atMost="6.03">6.03</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The emergence of superconductivity which competes with the SDW state at <measure type="interval"><num>4.18</num> ≤ P ≤ <num atMost="4.37">4.37</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> appears to be a general behaviour among (TMTCF) 2 X superconductors. The origin of SC of this group is considered to be produced by spin-fluctuation mediated Cooper pairs as discussed among heavy fermion systems since antiferro-magnetic spin fluctuation is developed in the normal state. Our data also supports that the spin fluctuation in the SDW state is enhanced by the formation of SC state. TMTTF salts have higher T c and higher P c than TMTSF salts. The higher T c is associated with the smaller band width due to the smaller transfer integrals, which increases density of states. This feature appears as the anion size dependency in β-BEDT-TTF group. 21</p>
        <p>There are <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> independent mechanisms for suppressing superconductivity with magnetic fields; one is orbital breaking of cooper pairs in the superconducting state associated with screening currents generated to exclude the external field (orbital limit) which becomes dominant first for most superconductors. The other mechanism is a spin effect due to Zeeman splitting which applies only to singlet pairings and limits superconductivity below the Pauli or Clongston-Chandrasekhar limit 22,23 , as given by weak-coupling BCS paramagnetic formula,</p>
        <p>where ∆ is the superconducting gap at T = <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> and µ B is Bohr magneton for isotropic s-wave pairing in the absence of spin-orbit scattering. This relation is a good guide to determine whether the system is a triplet superconductor or not. The anisotropy of H c2 in (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 was determined by Lee 24 . It was more than <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> times the Pauli limit and there was no change in the NMR night shift. These results supported the view that this system is a triplet superconductor. In the case of (TMTSF) ClO 4 , Yonezawa et al. 25 conclude that it is a singlet superconductor and exhibits an FFLO state in high fields.</p>
        <p>Aizawa et al. showed that consecutive transitions from singlet pairing to FFLO and further to Sz = <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> triplet pairing can generally take place upon increasing the magnetic field in the vicinity of the SDW+CDW coexisting phase, and they postulate (TMTSF) 2 X as a candidate material which exhibits this property.</p>
        <p>We studied how the superconducting transitions are affected by magnetic fields to get detailed information on H c2 and its anisotropy. Data of resistivity vs. temperature at P .64 GPa, respectively. By using the (WHH) formula 27 , the values of the <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>-temperature upper critical field H c2 (0) can be estimated by</p>
        <p>Taking T c = <measure type="list"><num>2.30</num>, <num>1.79</num></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>1.51</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>, we obtain <measure type="list"><num>1.36</num>, <num>1.01</num> and <num>0.47</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for corresponding pressures.</p>
        <p>We use this equation to fit our data to enhance the deviation from the orbital limiting where t a and t b are transfer integrals along a and b. 28 If you take a conservative estimate of the ratio t a /t b = <measure type="value"><num>4</num></measure>, it yields H F F LO P (0) ∼ 5T which seems to be a reasonable value for the FFLO limiting to occur however with the ratio we obtain from coherence length in this work, t a /t b ∼ <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num></measure>, yielding an FFLO limiting field of <measure type="value"><num>3.1</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> which is <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> smaller than the low temperature extrapolated value, H(0) ∼ <measure type="value"><num>4.5</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>. Further study is needed at lower temperature and also in the pressure range where spin density waves and superconductivity coexist to Therefore this feature seems universal among TMTCF salts.</p>
        <p>A characteristic value of superconductors is the coherence length, ξ. ξ is the spatial parameter for the wave function of the Cooper pair, and electrons within this length move while correlating with each other. We estimated the Ginzburg-Landau (GL) coherence lengths from the slope of H c2 for <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> directions near T c by using the following relations (Eq.4) for anisotropic superconductors (Table.I).</p>
        <p>where φ 0 is a flux quantum. ξ values increase monotonically with pressure. However, the coherence lengths are highly anisotropic, for example at P = <measure type="value"><num>5.64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, ξ a : ξ b : ξ c * ∼ <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>, the interlayer coherence length, ξ c * , is much longer than the thickness of the conducting sheet which is c/2 ∼ <measure type="value"><num>6.5</num><measure type="?" unit="Å">Å</measure></measure> where c is a lattice parameter of (TMTTF)</p>
        <p>We have conducted transport measurements by using a turnbuckle type DAC on (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 under multi-extreme conditions which had been difficult to achieve at the same time. (TMTTF) 2 X has higher critical pressure which exceeds the range of widely-used piston cylinder cells, and for this reason not many observations of superconductivity and that H c2 displays positive curvature without saturation which may be attributed to an FFLO state, for magnetic field along a-axis and b -axis in T≥<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.5">0.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for P = <measure type="value"><num>4.48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>.</p>
        <p>We also have shown that the upturn feature is suppressed with increasing pressure and the orbital pair breaking mechanism becomes dominant. In further studies on the pair breaking mechanism, measurements need to be conducted at lower temperatures and with more refined pressure control. Our data above T = <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> shows H c2 slightly exceed the Pauli paramagnetic limit at P = <measure type="value"><num>4.48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> for H//a. H c2 curves for H//a and H//b lie on top of each other indicating that it has <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-dimentional-like feature being isotropic within an a − b plane. GL coherence lengths were obtained and revealed that (TMTTF) PF 6 is anisotropic <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> dimensional superconductor.</p>
        <p>We wish to thank Dr. Y. Huseya for useful discussions. This work was supported by Technology (MEXT) of the Japanese Government, Grant-in-Aid For Scientific Research (21340092, 21740263, and 21110517) of JSPS of Japan. This work has been performed at the Institute for Solid State Physics, University of Tokyo.</p>
    </text>
</tei>