<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2020-09-01T09:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
        <p>Fe-based superconductors discovered in <measure type="value"><date when="2008">2008</date></measure> 1) have stimulated fundamental discussions on the mechanism of superconductivity. Among the Fe-based superconductors, 11-type compounds have the simplest structure consisting only of superconducting layers. On the other hand, the other Fe-based superconductors (111 type, 122 type, 1111 type, and so on) have a stacking structure with both superconducting layers and block layers. Thus, 11-type superconductors have been extensively studied in order to understand the mechanism of Fe-based superconductivity. The 11-type superconductor FeSe exhibits superconductivity with T c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> 2) and its T c reaches <measure type="value"><num>37</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> under high pressure (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4">4</num>-<num atMost="6">6</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>). 3,4) The pressure dependence of T c relates to the anion height from the Fe layers, 2) and T c of FeSe increases with decreasing anion (Se) height by high pressure. Thus, 11-type superconductors have the potential of achieving a high T c . Additionally, T c of K 0:8 Fe 2 Se 2 , composed of K intercalation between FeSe layers, also shows an abrupt increase above <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. 5) For (LiNH 2 ) x Fe 2 Se 2 , the superconductivity exhibits a higher T c of <measure type="value"><num>43</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. 6) With an increase in the c lattice parameter and the separation between Fechalcogen layers, T c increases. Therefore, a change of Fechalcogen layer has a great impact on superconductivity. Recently, it was reported that a FeSe monolayer synthesized by MBE method shows superconductivity at <measure type="value"><num>53</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. 7) -GGA (spin-dependent generalized gradient approximation) calculations have predicted that a Dirac-cone state appears in a FeSe monolayer. 8) The Dirac-cone states behind the superconducting state may substantially raise its T c . 9) Furthermore, there are several reports where the T c of superconducting ultrathin films become higher than that of the bulk. 10,11) Thus, an ultrathin film of 11-type compounds may show an abrupt increase in T c .</p>
        <p>Recently, it was reported that thin films of the 11-type superconductor FeTe 1Àx S x can be fabricated by the scotchtape method, 12) which is a powerful technique to easily prepare an ultrathin film such as graphene. 13) The structure of 11-type compounds is similar to that of graphite since each layer is connected by van-der-Waals forces. In addition, 11-type superconductors have no insulating block layers. Thus, the 11-type superconductors are ideal candidates for the fabrication of a superconducting monolayer film by the scotch-tape method. If we could obtain a monolayer or ultrathin film, it will give us a greater understanding of the superconducting mechanism. Additionally, a property which has not been observed for the bulk yet may appear by thinning. Thus, we fabricated the thin films and measured the resistivities.</p>
        <p>Single crystals of FeTe 0:65 Se 0:35 were synthesized by a self-flux method. Grains of Fe (<measure type="value"><num>99.9</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), Te (<measure type="value"><num>99.999</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), and Se (<measure type="value"><num>99.9999</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) were sealed into evacuated quartz tube with the desired molar ratio. Since the tube often cracks during cooling, it was sealed into a larger evacuated tube. The doubly-sealed materials were heated at <measure type="value"><num>1100</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="C">C</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> and then cooled about À2 C/h down to <measure type="value"><num>650</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="C">C</measure></measure> followed by furnace cooling. The obtained single crystal was placed on scotch tape, and cleaved several times. The scotch tape with the FeTe 0:65 Se 0:35 flakes were attached to a silicon substrate with a silicon dioxide layer on the top surface, and pressed to enhance the bonding between the crystals and the substrate by van-der-Waals forces. By this process, 12) thin single crystals were left on the substrate.</p>
        <p>An optical microscope and an atomic force microscope (AFM) were used to investigate the thin films fabricated by the scotch-tape method. We measured the resistivity of the thin films by a <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure>-terminal circuit fabricated using electron-beam lithography. In the process of electron-beam lithography, a resist was first spin-coated onto the substrates. The resist underwent a specially designed electron-beam scan routine in order to write electrode patterns. The irradiated area was removed by a developer, and then the electrode was deposited. The residual resist was finally taken off. By this technique, we prepared the <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure>-terminal electrodes. The width and separation of the terminals are <measure type="list"><num>2</num> and <num>3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>, respectively. indicate that a thin film with a flat surface can easily be obtained using the scotch-tape method. The thicknesses of these films were estimated to be <measure type="list"><num>15</num>, <num>65</num>, and <num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, respectively. From the comparison between the optical and AFM images, we found that the colors of the thin films are gradually paled out with decreasing thicknesses.</p>
        <p>The temperature dependence of resistivities of these films with thicknesses of <measure type="list"><num>15</num>, <num>65</num>, and <num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, and the bulk are different from each other, as shown in Fig. 2. The same onset superconducting transition temperature T on c of <measure type="value"><num>15.0</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> is observed for <measure type="list"><num>65</num>, <num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, and the bulk. However, the thin film with <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> thickness does not show a superconducting transition. The transition widths (ÁT c ) are ÁT c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:6</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>65</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, ÁT c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>1:0</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, and ÁT c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>6:5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for the bulk, respectively. The thin film with <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> thickness clearly shows a sharper superconducting transition than other films and the bulk. Furthermore, the normal-state resistivities above T c show not only metallic properties but also semiconductivity. The normal-state resistivities for <measure type="list"><num>65</num></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> slowly decreases with decreasing temperature while that for <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> and the bulk increases, as shown in Fig. 2(b). These results clearly show the inhomogeneous superconductivity in FeTe 1Àx Se x although these films were extracted from the same bulk sample.</p>
        <p>The variety of resistivity behavior may be attributed to the strain due to thinning. However, these films were extracted from the same bulk crystal where each layer is connected via van-der-Waals forces, and thus free from strain, compared to the films synthesized on substrates by deposition methods. Therefore, the inhomogeneous superconductivity cannot be explained by the strain. The broadening superconducting transition width and the change of the normal-state resistivity are similar to the excess Fe dependence of resistivity of Fe 1þd Te 1Àx Se x . 14,15) Therefore, the increase of the resistivity corresponds to weak charge carrier localization due to the excess Fe, which results in the broadening of superconducting transition for <measure type="value"><num>65</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> and the bulk. STM researches reported the inhomogeneous distribution of excess Fe and few chalcogen vacancies. 16,17) Our bulk sample has relatively broader ÁT c than previous reports. 14,15) The inhomogeneous superconductivity may depend on the quality of the sample. However, we could observe the quantum oscillations of the thin crystal extracted from the same bulk sample. 18) Quantum oscillation measurements are a powerful technique to estimate Fermi surfaces, but they have not been reported for the 11-type compounds yet. The reason is probably that a single crystal of 11-type compound is not homogeneous enough for quantum oscillation to be observed. Thus, the excess Fe makes the crystal inhomogeneous.</p>
        <p>The inhomogeneous distribution of excess Fe results in the inhomogeneities of superconductivity and normal-state resistivity. The result for <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, which shows metallic resistivity with sharpest ÁT c , suggests that a homogeneous crystal with a low quantity of excess Fe, that was originally part of the bulk, is cleaved and remains on the surface of the substrate incidentally. This indicates that a homogeneous crystal with low excess Fe can be obtained using the scotchtape method and shows ideal superconductivity. On the other hand, the result for <measure type="value"><num>65</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> implies that a part of the crystal with some excess Fe remains on the substrate and its superconductivity is slightly inhibited by the excess Fe. For <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, a part of the crystal with a large excess of Fe remains and does not exhibits the superconductivity and metallic resistivity. Additionally, we determined the upper critical field H c2 ðT Þ curves of the thin film with <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> thickness for H k c axis and the H k ab plane from the temperature dependence of the resistivity under a magnetic field. The temperature dependence of the resistivity under a magnetic field is summarized in Fig. 3 for (a) the H k c axis and (b) H k ab plane. The temperature at which the resistivity reached <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> was systematically suppressed with increasing magnetic field. We estimated H c2 ðT Þ from the criterion of <measure type="value"><num>90</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of normal-state resistivity. From the comparison of H c2 ðT Þ for the thin film with bulk, H c2 ðT Þ curves of the thin film shift toward higher field than those of the bulk. Moreover, we calculated the H ab c2 ð0Þ and H c c2 ð0Þ using the data from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num> to <num atMost="7">7</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> and Werthamer-Helfand-Hohenberg (WHH) theory: 19) H ab c2 ð0Þ ¼ 134:3 T and H c c2 ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>90:6</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for the thin film, and H ab c2 ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>87:9</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> and H c c2 ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>39:2</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for the bulk. We also estimated the irreversibility field from the criterion of <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of normal-state resistivity, as shown in Fig. 3</p>
        <p>irr ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>102:6</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> and H c irr ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>45:6</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for the film, and H ab irr ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>53:9</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> and H c irr ð0Þ ¼ <measure type="value"><num>27:7</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for the bulk. The H irr for the film are much larger than that of the bulk and in previous reports. 20,21) The anisotropy coefficients determined from ¼ H ab c2 ð0Þ=H c c2 ð0Þ were estimated to be <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num></measure> for the thin film and <measure type="value"><num>2.2</num></measure> for the bulk, respectively. The anisotropy coefficient of the thin film shows more isotropic behavior than that of the bulk. We found that the film with the lowest ÁT c exhibits more isotropic , high H c2 and H irr . In previous reports, the bulk sample with low excess Fe shows a lower ÁT c than compared with high excess Fe. 14) Excess Fe induces the broadening of ÁT c , worse superconducting properties, and more anisotropic behavior than ideal FeTe 1Àx Se x . Therefore, our results indicate that ideal FeTe 1Àx Se x bulk should exhibit high a superconducting performance with isotropic superconductivity and has an advantage for practical applications.</p>
        <p>In summary, we have fabricated thin films of FeTe 0:65 -Se 0:35 using the scotch-tape method, and measured the resistivities of the thin films and the bulk sample. The different superconductivities in the thin films and the bulk were observed in spite of the films extracted from same bulk sample. The result clearly shows that FeTe 1Àx Se x crystal is inhomogeneous by location. The inhomogeneity comes from the excess Fe concentration by location. The resistivity of a thin film with low excess Fe shows that the low excess Fe induces the lowest ÁT c , high H c2 and H irr .</p>
    </text>
</tei>