<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2020-09-01T09:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="lexicon/en">
        <p>We have measured the temperature-dependent resistivity of (TMTTF) PF 6 up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="7">7</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> using a turnbuckle-type diamond anvil cell (DAC) and at magnetic fields of up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>. Unlike previous reports on organic compounds, a <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistance was observed in the superconducting state even at high pressures. Superconductivity was observed in the range of P ¼ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.18">4:18</num> to <num atMost="6.03">6.03</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> and showed a peak T c of <measure type="value"><num>2.25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> at <measure type="value"><num>4.58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The temperature dependence of the upper critical magnetic field H c2 ðT Þ was determined via resistivity at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, for the intrachain (a), interchain (b 0), and interlayer (c Ã) configurations, and H c2 ðT Þ displays a positive curvature without saturation. This could be related to the wide pressure range of the coexistence between the spin density wave (SDW) and superconductivity (SC) ground state, and may be caused by an FFLO state, for a magnetic field along the a-and b 0-axes with T ! <measure type="value"><num>0:5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE">K</measure></measure> for P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. This feature is suppressed with increasing pressure when the orbital pair breaking mechanism becomes dominant. The Ginzburg-Landau coherence lengths for <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> different axes obtained from this work show that (TMTTF) PF 6 is an anisotropic <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-dimensional superconductor.</p>
        <p>The Bechgaard salt (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 (TMTSF = tetramethyltetraselenafulvalene) was the first organic superconductor discovered in <measure type="value"><date when="1980">1980</date></measure> with a superconducting temperature of T c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>0:9</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> (critical pressure, P c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>1:2</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>). 1) Since this discovery, materials based on TMTSF and its derivatives, such as TMTTF (tetramethyltetrathiofulvalene), the so-called (TMTCF) 2 X (X = monovalent anion) series, have been investigated extensively to search for other superconducting behaviors. [2][3][4][5] They have also attracted attention owing to their rich properties such as spin-Peierls (SP), charge-ordering, spin density wave (SDW), and possible unconventional superconductivity (SC) that appear by changing the counter anion or by applying external pressure. 6) Many compounds with TMTSF molecules exhibit an SC state at low pressures of approximately <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, 6,7) whereas most compounds with TMTTF exhibit an SC transition at ultra high pressures, for example, P c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> in (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 . 8,9) Taking advantage of the low pressure induced 10) and <measure type="value"><measure type="PRESSURE">ambient pressure</measure></measure> 11,12) superconductivity, studies especially of the SC phase and its upper critical field have been conducted extensively with TMTSF salts, but rarely with TMTTF salts.</p>
        <p>A generic phase diagram was obtained through studies of many different materials among the TMTCF series at ambient and high pressures, combining the trends seen with chemical and external pressures. 3,5,7) The (chemical) pressure that each material displays in the phase diagram shows the degrees of <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-dimensionality caused by many factors such as the size of the anion, the distance between molecular planes, distance between selenium or sulfur atoms and the Coulomb repulsion between conducting electrons. However, for layered organic materials such as TMTCF salts, the a-axis direction is most compressive where TMTCF planes have a weak van der Waals bonding due to the overlapping orbitals; it is least compressive along the c-axis direction where the TMTCF molecule and anion have ion bonding, even though the applied external pressure is highly hydrostatic. In the case of (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 , the lattice parameter a is decreased by <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>/kbar, while the normal directions are one order of magnitude less compressive <measure type="interval"><num atMost="13">13</num></measure>) when <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="kbar">kbar</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>0.3</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>) of hydrostatic pressure is applied. Therefore, even with hydrostatic pressure, the electronic structure changes anisotropically; the dimensionality of the system also changes, and the amplitude of the change varies depending on the size of the anion and the type of cation. It is an open question whether chemical pressure and external pressure can be treated in exactly the same manner. Therefore, by changing the external pressure on different designer molecules to gather information, one expects to achieve a universal understanding of quasi-one-dimensional organic conductors.</p>
        <p>Owing to the technical difficulty in applying hydrostatic pressure to fragile organic compounds at low temperatures in magnetic fields, the anisotropy of the upper critical field (H c2 ) in TMTTF salts had not been determined prior to this work. In the present work, the anisotropy of H c2 in (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 was determined via resistivity at tempera-tures as low as T ¼ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0:5">0:5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> and at magnetic fields of up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>, which also complements previous reports. 9,14) 2. Experimental Procedure Single crystals of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 were synthesized by the electrochemical method. 15) The dimensions of the crystal selected for resistivity measurements were <measure type="value"><num>$150 Â 30 Â 20</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="m 3">m 3</measure></measure> . The electrical resistivity was measured by the standard <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure>-probe method with an AC current range from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure> to A parallel to the a-axis (intrachain). This measurement was carried out in a He refrigerator located in a <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> magnet. Pressure was generated using a turnbuckle-type diamond anvil cell (DAC). The diamond culets are <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> in diameter and separated by a gasket indented to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="65">65</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> that has a <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> hole as a sample chamber. Details of this pressure apparatus are discussed elsewhere. 16) Graphite paint was used to make electrical contacts between the leads of pressed gold wires (<measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> in diameter) and the sample. The sample was placed inside a cavity with a liquid pressure medium, glycerin, which was proven to transmit a nearly hydrostatic pressure of up to GPa, 17) in the gasket, which is placed between the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> diamonds. The pressure is calibrated at T ¼ <measure type="value"><num>77</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE">K</measure></measure> by monitoring the shift in the fluorescence of a ruby chip located in the cavity near the sample. 18) The DAC used in this study tends to gain pressure as it is cooled down from room temperature to a temperature below liquid nitrogen temperature where the pressure stabilizes. During the measurements of H k b 0 , the sample in a DAC was warmed up to a temperature above the liquid nitrogen temperature a few times, which induced different normal state resistances. It is extremely difficult to calculate the absolute value of resistivity by transport measurement when using a DAC with organic materials. This is due to the amount of conducting paint, which is relatively large for a small sample, and the inaccurate determination of the distance between contacts and the cross sectional area of the sample. Therefore, we used the data from the resistivity measurement of a crystal from the same batch using a cubic anvil press for pressurization to normalize our data. 14) The pressure dependence of the resistivity at T ¼ <measure type="value"><num>285</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE">K</measure></measure> obtained using the cubic anvil press shows a range from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.04">0.04</num>-<num atMost="0.0015">0.0015</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> as the pressure is increased from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>-<num atMost="10">10</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. These values were used to determine the resistivity in the DAC.</p>
        <p>A magnetic field was applied along the a-, b 0 -, and c Ã -axes and the temperature dependence of the resistivity was measured in the pressure range of P ¼ <measure type="value"><num atLeast="4.37">4:37</num>{<num atMost="5.64">5:64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> at low temperatures. The orientation of the sample was adjusted by changing the angles of the DAC for each measurement point.</p>
        <p>The temperature dependence of the resistivity of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 is shown in a log-log plot for <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.79">0:79</num> P <num atMost="6.96">6:96</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> (Fig. 1). The local minimum of resistivity observed at approximately <measure type="value"><num>240</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>0:79</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> disappears with pressure application. The insulating behavior is gradually suppressed at higher pressures, and a metallic temperature dependence appears in the high-temperature range, followed by a low-temperature insulating behavior above P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>2:55</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The metal-insulator (M-I) transition temperature shifts to lower values as pressure is increased and reaches <measure type="value"><num>8.6</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:18</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The resistivity in the insulating region shows a sharp drop mediated by the SC transition at approximately <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>4.18</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The highest SC transition temperature is T c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>2:25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> at <measure type="value"><num>4.58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, and no SC transition was observed above P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>6:96</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. We define the local minimum temperature at <measure type="value"><num>0.79</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> as T , and estimated T s from the local minimum of @ ln ðT Þ=@T , where ðT Þ is the temperature-dependent resistivity.</p>
        <p>T c was defined by the onset temperature of the sharp drop of resistivity (see arrows in Fig. 1). Figure 2 highlights the low-temperature SC transition. Within the temperature range in the present work, the presence of <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistance was confirmed at approximately <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> in the pressure range of 4:18 P 4:<measure type="value"><num>58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, which was not previously observed. 8,9) This supports the hypothesis that the pressures generated in the DAC used here are as hydrostatic as those of a cubic anvil press, which was the only pressure apparatus that allowed <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistance to be observed in this material. 14) The finite width of the SC transition is considered a fluctuation effect in a low-dimensional system. The fluctuation effect associated with transitions cannot be ignored in low-dimensional systems; the superconductivity is destroyed at a finite temperature, producing a finite resistance. This resistance decreases exponentially as temperature drops, so the decrease in the resistance is clearly shown right below the T c . This is considered as the origin of the broad transition in our case, and this behavior is typical of organic superconductors. With increased pressure, even broader transitions are observed, probably owing to the suppression of spin fluctuations which will be discussed later in this section. Hump structures seen below T c have not been observed in earlier works. 8,9,14) We attribute these structures to an inhomogeneous SC state that probably results from structural deformation by nonuniform pressures generated by the DAC, and/or form microcracks due to the extremely brittle nature of the sample. The inhomogeneous state is not an intrinsic property.</p>
        <p>In a generic pressure-temperature (P-T ) phase diagram, 3,5,19) the ground state of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 becomes an AF/SDW from SP at approximately <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, and then an SC phase at approximately <measure type="value"><num>4.3</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The local minimum of the resistance appears at approximately <measure type="value"><num>400</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> at <measure type="value"><measure type="PRESSURE">ambient pressure</measure></measure>; this is referred to as the charge localized (CL) or Mott transition. Using these values, T and T s are defined by the gap formations of CL and SDW, respectively. Figure 3 shows the P-T phase diagram obtained in this work. Note that open symbols represent data cited from ref. 20 to show the likely regions of CL and SP. With increasing pressure, the nesting of the Fermi surface is broken and the SDW phase is suppressed. T s drops drastically at approximately P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> and disappears at the critical pressure of approximately P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:5</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. This is also clearly seen at higher pressures, where the normal state appears to be metallic at <measure type="value"><num>4.58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> and slightly localized at <measure type="value"><num>4.37</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> (Fig. 3). Above P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:37</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, metallic behavior is observed over the entire temperature range. The highest T c was observed near the pressure at which the SDW phase vanished. The SC phase in the vicinity of the SDW phase was observed at <measure type="value"><num atLeast="4.18">4:18</num> P <num atMost="6.03">6:03</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The emergence of superconductivity, which competes with the SDW state at <measure type="value"><num atLeast="4.18">4:18</num> P <num atMost="4.37">4:37</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, appears to be a general behavior among (TMTCF) 2 X superconductors. The origin of superconductivity in this family is considered to be produced by spin fluctuations developed in Cooper pairs similar to heavyfermion systems 21) since an antiferro-magnetic spin fluctuation develops in the normal state. Our data also supports the theory that the spin fluctuation in the SDW state is enhanced by the formation of an SC state. TMTTF salts have a higher T c and a higher P c than TMTSF salts. The higher T c is a result of the smaller bandwidth due to the smaller transfer integrals, which in turn increases the density of states. This feature appears as the anion size dependence for the -BEDT-TTF group. 22)</p>
        <p>There are <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> independent mechanisms of suppressing superconductivity with magnetic fields. One is the orbital breaking of Cooper pairs in the superconducting state associated with screening currents generated to exclude the external field (orbital limit), which becomes dominant first for most superconductors. The other is a spin effect due to Zeeman splitting, which applies only to singlet pairings and limits superconductivity below the Pauli or Clogston-Chandrasekhar limit, 23,24) as given by the weak-coupling BCS paramagnetic formula</p>
        <p>where Á 0 is the superconducting gap at T ¼ <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE">K</measure></measure> and B is Bohr magneton for isotropic s-wave pairing in the absence of spin-orbit scattering. This relation is a good guide for determining whether or not the system is a triplet superconductor. The anisotropy of H c2 in (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 was determined by Lee et al. 25) The magnitude of H c2 was more than <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> times the Pauli limit and there was no change in the NMR Knight shift. These results supported the view that this system is a triplet superconductor. However, after that, a clear change of the Knight shift was observed for the superconductivity of (TMTSF) 2 ClO 4 at T c , revealing that it is in the singlet state at lower fields. 26) Yonezawa et al. 27) concluded that (TMTSF) ClO 4 is a singlet superconductor and exhibits an FFLO state at high fields by a careful study of the in-plane anisotropy of T c . Aizawa et al. showed that consecutive transitions from the singlet pairing to the FFLO state and further to the S z ¼ 1 triplet pairing can generally take place upon increasing the magnetic field in the vicinity of the SDW+CDW coexisting phase; they also postulated (TMTSF) 2 X as a candidate material that exhibits this property. 28) Data of resistivity vs temperature at P ¼ 4:<measure type="value"><num>37{4:58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> and with the field along <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> different axes are shown in Fig. 4. For H k a and c Ã , the resistivity in the normal state at <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> applied field does not vary as the magnetic field is increased, and the transition temperatures are depressed to lower values. For H k b 0 at P ¼ <measure type="list"><num>4:37</num> and <num>4.96</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, the pressures rose by approximately <measure type="value"><num>0.4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> during the thermal cycling owing to the differential contraction of the pressure cell. It only happens for H k b 0 , as it was the first orientation measured after each pressurization. The effect of the change in pressure on the normal state resistivity becomes obvious near the critical pressure; therefore, it can only be seen at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:37</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The pressure rose from <measure type="value"><num>4.37</num></measure> to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="4.58">4.58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> during this particular measurement for H k b 0 . This explains the higher resistance in Fig. 4(b) than in Figs. 4(a) and 4(c). Also a small localization can be seen in the curves for H ¼ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>{<num atMost="0.19">0:19</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>, and an even smaller localization in the curves for H ¼ <measure type="value"><num atLeast="0.29">0:29</num>{<num atMost="1.59">1:59</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>. In our measured temperature range, no SC was detected above <measure type="value"><num>2.2</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> along the a-and b 0 -axes and above <measure type="value"><num>0.39</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for the c Ã -axis. Figure 5 shows the temperature dependence of H c2 (resistive onset) at P ¼ <measure type="list"><num>4:58</num>, <num>5.23</num> and <num>5.64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> for H k a. The slopes of H c2 ðT Þ near T c , i.e., dH c2 =dT were <measure type="list"><num>0.86</num>, <num>0.77</num>, and <num>0.37</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> K À1 for P ¼ <measure type="list"><num>4:58</num>, <num>5.23</num>, and <num>5.64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, respectively. By using the Werthamer-Helfand-Hohenberg (WHH) formula, 29) the <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>-temperature upper critical fields H c2 ð0Þ can be estimated using</p>
        <p>Taking T c ¼ <measure type="list"><num>2:30</num>, <num>1.79</num>, and <num>1.51</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>, we obtain <measure type="list"><num>1.36</num>, <num>1.01</num>, and <num>0.47</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure> for their corresponding pressures. In the Ginzburg-Landau (GL) theory, H c2 ¼ È 0 =2 2 , where is the coherence length and is proportional to ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ð1 þ t 2 Þ=ð1 À t 2 Þ p , È 0 is the flux quantum, and t ¼ T =T c is the reduced temperature. Combining terms gives</p>
        <p>This equation is used to fit our data to enhance the deviation from the orbital limiting boundary; they are shown in Fig. 5 as the dashed lines. A slightly higher H c2 ð0Þ was achieved by the GL theoretical fit [eq. 3 superconductor in our measured temperature and magnetic field ranges. Lebed estimated the FFLO field at <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> temperature to be H FFLO P ð0Þ ' 0:6 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi t a =t b p H P where t a and t b are the transfer integrals along a and b, respectively. 30) A conservative estimate of the ratio t a =t b 0 ¼ 4 yields H FFLO P ð0Þ $ <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION">T</measure></measure>, which seems to be a reasonable value for the FFLO limiting to occur. However, with the ratio we obtained from the coherence length in this work, t a =t b 0 $ <measure type="value"><num>1:5</num></measure>, yielding an FFLO limiting field of <measure type="value"><num>3.1</num> <measure type="MAGNETIC_INDUCTION" unit="T">T</measure></measure>, which is <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> smaller than the low-temperature-extrapolated value, Hð0Þ $ 4:5 T. Therefore, the upward curvature from the GL determination that appeared in the H c2 ðT Þ curve at P ¼ 4:<measure type="value"><num>58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> below T ¼ <measure type="value"><num>1:64</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> and at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>5:23</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> below T ¼ <measure type="value"><num>1:01</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> may be the result of an FFLO state.</p>
        <p>Another possible interpretation for this upturn, particularly for the H c2 ðT Þ curve at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, could be related to the wide pressure range of the coexistence between the SDW and SC ground states as observed for H k c Ã in (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 . 25) For a thin superconducting layer, the upper critical field in a field parallel to the layer is greatly enhanced with the relation H c2 $ ð=dÞH c , where d is the layer thickness, is the penetration depth, and H c is the thermodynamic critical field. 31) In the new model proposed by Lee et al., the formation and reconstruction of SDW/ superconductor domains occur taking advantage of the largest penetration depth. 25) Their model seems to be consistent with our data since the deviation from the GL fit decreases as the pressure increases or as the system is moved further from the SDW phase.</p>
        <p>The anisotropies of H c2 for P ¼ <measure type="list"><num>4:48</num>, <num>5.10</num>, and <num>5.64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> obtained using the onset criterion is shown in Fig. 6. Owing to the difficulty in achieving exactly the same pressure at low temperatures for each thermal cycle, the plots for all the axes that show similar T c values at <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> field are compared in the same figure, even though the pressures are slightly different. The pressure difference is less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="3">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. A positive curvature without saturation as T decreases can be seen for H k a and H k b 0 , and the curves for H k a and H k b 0 are almost on top of each other at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> in this temperature range. Interestingly, a similar trend is observed in (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 25) and (TMTSF) 2 ClO 4 ; 27) H a c2 ðT Þ % H b 0 c2 ðT Þ ) H c Ã c2 ðT Þ, except in the absence of isotropic features in the low field range in the present work. However, H c2 ðT Þ curves were anisotropic in the ab 0 -plane in the case of (TMTSF) SbF 6 , which will be published elsewhere. When the field is applied along the c Ã -axis, orbital limiting dominates because the field penetrates the ab 0 -plane and decouples the Cooper pairs. However it is unusual for the curve of H k b 0 to be on top of H k a, not showing any anisotropy at all where the transfer integral t b 0 is smaller than t a by <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> order of magnitude at <measure type="value"><measure type="PRESSURE">ambient pressure</measure></measure>.</p>
        <p>Also a complete structural study of (TMTSF) 2 PF 6 and (TMTSF) 2 ClO 4 up to approximately <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> was reported by Gallois et al. 33) The ab-plane anisotropy could be predicted using the independent molecular mean distances between TMTSF molecules in intra-and inter-chains. The interchain distances were better compressed than the intrachain distances from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.01">0.01</num></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>0.98</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. The spacial distance between Se atoms in the b-axis were only about <measure type="value"><num>0.16</num></measure> # A longer than that in the a-axis at <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. In our case, we applied a very high pressure for (TMTTF) PF 6 , so that the anisotropy in ab 0 -plane at <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> will be well suppressed. However, the use of different types of pressure apparatus markedly affects the change in crystal structure. Furthermore, the present data imply a large pressure effect in resistivity up to P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:37</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, as seen in Fig. 1. One may consider from this isotropy that paramagnetic limiting dominates for both orientations, but as can be seen in Figs. 6(b) and 6(c), similar curves appear at higher pressures where the orbital limiting clearly dominates. Therefore, this feature seems universal among TMTCF salts. A characteristic parameter of superconductors is the coherence length . is the spatial parameter for the wave function of Cooper pairs, and electrons within this length move while correlating with each other. We estimated the GL coherence lengths, which give the length scale over which the superconducting order parameter may change from the slope of H c2 for <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> axes near T c using the following relation [eq. 4] for anisotropic superconductors (Table I):</p>
        <p>where 0 is the flux quantum and increases monotonically with pressure. However, the coherence lengths are highly anisotropic, for example, at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>5:64</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, a : b 0 : c Ã $ <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>, the interlayer coherence length c Ã is much larger than the thickness of the conducting sheet for all pressures, which is c=2 $ <measure type="value"><num>6:5</num> # <measure type="CURRENT" unit="A">A</measure></measure>, where c is a lattice parameter of (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 . These results indicate that the present compound is an anisotropic <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-dimensional superconductor that does not involve Josephson interaction. Note that these values might be underestimated owing to contribution of the paramagnetic limiting effect leading H c2 to have a smaller slope. Therefore, the coherence length for P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> could be slightly smaller if paramagnetic limiting is completely eliminated; however, it should not affect this estimation. As seen in Fig. 5 for <measure type="value"><num>4.48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>, the upturn behavior in H c2 towards low temperatures is often considered as the field-induced dimensional crossover (FIDC) from 3D to 2D, but the calculated c Ã shows that there is no FIDC. In the anisotropic 3D model, GL coherence lengths are associated with effective masses, and anisotropy is defined as</p>
        <p>We used ac Ã ¼ a = c Ã and b 0 c Ã ¼ b 0 = c Ã in our case, and obtained the anisotropy and ratio of effective masses that are shown in Table I. The ratio of transfer integrals along each axis are estimated to be t a : t b 0 : t c Ã ¼ <measure type="value"><num>300</num></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> : <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> at <measure type="value"><measure type="PRESSURE">ambient pressure</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><measure type="TEMPERATURE">room temperature</measure></measure>, whereas according to our data, within the pressure and temperature range superconductivity is observed, the strong one-dimensional feature is suppressed and dimensionality is increased. The conductivities along the a-and b 0 -axes are about the same and larger than that of the c Ã -axis by a factor of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>-<num atMost="30">30</num></measure>. With increasing pressure, m c Ã increases. This is consistent with the results of Morosin et al., 13) given that the compressibility is smaller along the c Ã -axis where a TMTTF molecule and an anion form an ionic bond than along the a-axis where orbits of TMTTF are overlapped with a van der Waals bonding. Also note that a superconductivity appeared with uniaxial strain along the a-axis but not with that perpendi-cular to the a-axis in the case of (TMTSF) PF 6 . These results implied that compression along the a-axis direction leads to an increase in interchain transfer integrals with a reduction in the diagonal distance of TMTSF molecules. [34][35][36]</p>
        <p>We have conducted transport measurement by using a turnbuckle-type DAC on (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 under multi-extreme conditions which was previously difficult to achieve. (TMTTF) 2 X has a higher critical pressure exceeding the range of widely used piston cylinder cells, and for this reason few observations of superconductivity have been reported. We have observed superconductivity in (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 with an actual <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistivity at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num atLeast="4.18">4:18</num>{<num atMost="4.58">4:58</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. In this compound, <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistivity was never observed in the SC phase in other high pressure studies using a regular DAC or Bridgman pressure cell (BAC) with a solid pressure medium. However, better results, including <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistivity in the SC state, have been obtained recently in BAC with a liquid pressure medium in (TMTTF) BF 4 . 37) In (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 , only measurements with a cubic anvil press, which generates highly hydrostatic pressures, showed superconductivity with <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> resistivity, 14) indicating that our measurement with a DAC has similar accuracy to that with a cubic anvil press. The SC dome lies at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num atLeast="4.18">4:18</num>{<num atMost="6.18">6:18</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> in the P-T phase diagram obtained from this work, and the highest transition temperature was T c ¼ <measure type="value"><num>2:25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. Our data extended the ranges of temperatures and pressures and supplemented the reported P-T phase diagram.</p>
        <p>We have also measured the temperature dependence of H c2 along the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> axes on (TMTTF) PF 6 and shown that H c2 displays a positive curvature without saturation, which may be attributed to an FFLO state, for a magnetic field along the a-and b 0 -axes at T ! <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0:5">0:5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> for P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure>. We also have shown that the upturn feature is suppressed with increasing pressure and the orbital pair breaking mechanism becomes dominant. In further studies of the pair breaking mechanism, measurement should be conducted at lower temperatures and with more refined pressure control. Our data above T ¼ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.5">0:5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> shows that H c2 slightly exceeds the Pauli paramagnetic limit at P ¼ <measure type="value"><num>4:48</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="GPa">GPa</measure></measure> for H k a. H c2 curves for H k a and H k b 0 lie on top of each other indicating that it has a <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-dimensional-like feature, being isotropic within the ab 0 -plane. GL coherence lengths were obtained; they revealed that (TMTTF) 2 PF 6 is anisotropic <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-dimensional superconductor. Table I. Slopes of H c2 curve near T c (dH=dT ), coherence lengths (), anisotropies (), and ratios of effective masses (m Ã a : m Ã b 0 : m Ã c Ã ). See text for details. P (GPa)</p>
        <p>We wish to thank Dr. Y. Fuseya for helpful discussions. This work was supported by the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan (MEXT) through Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research (Nos. 21340092, 21740263, and 21110517).</p>
    </text>
</tei>